<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Copyright (C) 2000-2006 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p4/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="intro-eps-html" rend="integral" xml:lang="fr">
    <head>Introduction pour les épigraphistes</head>
    <p>Les principes sous tendant EpiDoc rassemblent, pour les épigraphistes, des concepts traditionels et des méthodes d'édition et des conventions tout à fait nouvelles.</p>
    <div xml:id="IntroEpigraphers-conventions">
        <head>Conventions épigraphiques</head>
        <p> Au cours du siècle dernier, les épigraphistes ont été confrontés aux problèmes liés à la représentation d'informations non verbales dans leurs textes écrits. 
			Les éditeurs ont, jusqu'à la fin du 19ème siècle, produit des facsimile des textes mais cette pratique devint ensuite de plus en plus rare, les éditeurs montrant
			en outre peu d'empressement à remplacer ces facsimile par des reproductions photographiques intégrales de chaque document. 
			Des conventions furent par ailleurs (et non sans mal) dévelopées pour représenter les zones de texte manquantes, les abbréviations, etc., et sont globallement 
			acceptées par tous depuis les années 1930, partageant nombre de points communs avec celles développées en papyrologie et en paléographie. 
			Tous les épigraphistes ont depuis été confrontés aux conséquences du passage à l'informatique, notamment la difficulté de reproduire ces conventions, notamment 
			la difficulté de trouver une police permettant de mettre un point sous un caractère. Cependant la plupart ont désormais surmonté ces obstacles. 
		</p>
        <p>
		Les difficultées posées par ces questions, en particulier le rendu des caractères grecs avec des polices complètes et affichables sur le web, ont généralement 
		ralentit la publication en ligne de textes épigraphiques. En lieu et place sont apparues des bases de données d'une grande richesse, parmi lesquelles :
		
			<list type="unordered">
                <item>the <ref target="http://www.eagle-eagle.it">Electronic Archive of Greek and Latin Epigraphy (EAGLE)</ref> et les bases de données qui la composent, projet mené sous la conduitre de l'Association Internationale d'Epigraphie Grecque et Latine (AIEGL): 
					<list type="unordered">
                        <item>
                            <ref target="http://www.edb.uniba.it/">Epigraphic Database Bari (EDB)</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="http://www.uni-heidelberg.de/institute/sonst/adw/edh/" xml:lang="de">Epigraphische Datenbank Heidelberg (EDH)</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="http://www.edr-edr.it/">Epigraphic Database Roma (EDR)</ref>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </item>
                <item>La collection de textes grecs du Packard Humanities Institute <ref target="http://epigraphy.packhum.org/inscriptions/" n="PHI Greek Epigraphic Texts Online">disponible en ligne</ref> depuis 2005.</item>
            </list>
        </p>
        <p>Se référer également à: <ref target="conformance.xml">Compatibilité d'EpiDoc</ref>.</p>
		
        <p>
			Tous ces développements ont en outre été déterminés par l'état de l'art technologique au moment de leur mise en oeuvre, l'informatique ayant connu
			d'importantes évolutions au cours du 20ème siècle. L'objectif d'EpiDoc est d'exploiter ces nouvelles technologies pour poursuivre les objectifs 
			tradionnels de l'épigraphie par de nouveaux moyens. 
			Nombre des processus évoqués plus haut ont impliquer de lutter contre des limitations technologiques (notamment dans le domaine de l'impression papier)
			afin de répondre au plus grand nombre de besoins des épigraphiques. Avec le temps il est devenu de plus en plus difficile de persuader les imprimeurs 
			classiques d'accepter les besoins spécifiques d'insertion d'information méta-textuelles, sauf à payer des tarifs exhorbitants. 
			Et ce alors même que la quantité d'information accompagnant chaque texte a grandement augmenté : outre les informations sur l'apparence physique ou 
			les circonstances de découverte, la représentation photographique des documents étant également standard. 
		</p>
        <p>
			Les quinze dernières années ont vu les chercheurs affronter des problèmes généralements similaires en terme d'intégration de métadonnées au sein 
			de leurs textes en format électronique et divers outils ont rendu ces tâches de plus en plus aisée et les résulats de plus en plus bénéfiques. 
			
			In the last 15 years scholars generally have been dealing with similar requirements to incorporate meta-data within texts in their
            electronic form, and tools have emerged which make this increasingly easy and make the results increasingly valuable. The word-processing
            software that has been familiar since the 1980s allows us to control the formatting of our texts, using markup which by now is invisibly
            embedded by the software. The more demanding requirements of large-scale document collections - legal papers, industrial documentation,
            commercial publishing - led in the 1980s to the investigation of ways to insert a wider range of information and instructions within
            electronic texts. At first the emphasis was on inserting formatting instructions, but there soon emerged methods of including more complex
            semantic information concerning document structure and even content. A simple example is marking up a book title as a title, rather than
            simply marking it as being italicized. The use of this more abstract markup permits a separation of structure and presentation, where
            structure is comparatively fundamental to the document's genre, while presentation may be varied depending on the form of publication. In
            a way, this shift represents a return to an earlier mode in which authors dealt with the substance of the text and all details of
            presentation were handled in the publishing process - a distinction which has been lost in the days of camera-ready copy.</p>
        <p>The protocols which emerged from this latter effort were standardized in the late 1980s as the Standard Generalized Markup Language, and
            more recently were given a simpler and more flexible form for use in the world-wide web as XML: the <ref target="http://www.w3.org/XML/">Extensible Markup Language</ref>. XML is now widely used by scholars in a broad range of humanistic disciplines to capture/represent
            and preserve research materials for a wide range of purposes.</p>
        <p>The attractions of XML for epigraphers are therefore considerable. For example: missing material can be marked up as such, and then
            presented within square brackets; at the same time, a search can be instructed only to interrogate text which has not been marked up as
            missing (so only definitely attested terms). Uncertain letters can be marked up as such, and a decision made later as to whether to render
            them with an underdot or in another way. Words can be lemmatised during editing, to create indices which grow as the collection grows.
            What is important, however, at this juncture is to repeat the 'Leyden' exercise; that is, to agree electronic equivalents of the various
            sigla that we use. Firstly, this is valuable simply in order to save time and trouble; but also consistency - without imposing uniformity
            - continues to be valuable. Not only does it support the user, as on the printed page; but documents edited in this way and published
            electronically will then be exploitable together, even if they have been prepared separately.</p>
        <p>The need for agreed standards is not limited to epigraphy. Since 1987 an international consortium of scholars principally in the humanities
            has been working together to develop and refine a set of guidelines for describing the structure and content of documents. The results of
            this endeavour have produced an encoding language, realized in XML and described by the name of the group - TEI, the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiatve</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="IntroEpigraphers-TEI">
        <head>TEI for Epigraphers: What is it, why use it?</head>
        <p>The Text Encoding Initiative is a research effort aimed at defining an encoding language that encompasses the needs of humanities scholars
            very generally. There are two essential goals motivating the development of the TEI. The first is to enable scholars to represent their
            research materials in digital form using a descriptive language that mirrors the kinds of analytical terms and concepts that are familiar
            and essential to humanistic scholarship. The second goal is to enable scholars to share the resulting materials intelligibly, by using a
            common descriptive language. </p>
        <p>We can think of the TEI encoding language as resembling a human language: a core of shared terms at the center, surrounded by less widely
            shared vocabularies including local usage, specialized terminology, and other variations. At the core of the TEI are the common terms and
            concepts that are broadly shared by scholars in most disciplines: features like paragraphs, generic textual divisions, headings, lists,
            and so forth. More specialized elements are grouped together according to their applications: for instance, elements for detailed encoding
            of names, elements for representing features of manuscripts, elements for capturing the structure of dictionaries, and so forth. The TEI
            is intentionally organized into modules in this way, so that scholars working in specific disciplinary areas may use only the modules
            relevant to their work, and omit the others. The TEI can thus achieve a great deal of breadth without burdening individual scholars and
            projects with the necessity of mastering a very large domain, much of which is only relevant to other disciplines. On the contrary, the
            TEI encoding language can be very directly targeted at a specific domain or task, and can be limited to what is essential to the
            individual project's work. </p>
        <p>Like a human language, TEI can be used in a way that draws on a rich and nuanced vocabulary, with detailed encoding that describes a great
            many textual phenomena, but it can also be used very simply, using only a few essential concepts that describe only the most basic textual
            facts: sections, headings, paragraphs. The more detailed the encoding, the more one can do with it, but factors such as time, cost,
            available staff, and local expertise may place constraints on the level of detail that is feasible. </p>
        <p>In addition to providing an encoding system that scholars can use in its original state, the TEI also provides a way for scholarly projects
            to define custom versions of the TEI language which include modifications that are necessary to support specific local needs. Because
            these custom versions operate within the overall TEI framework, they can use its broadly shared core of terms and concepts, thereby
            avoiding unnecessary work in reinventing these. And because the TEI provides a common framework for creating and describing
            customizations, these can be shared easily and meaningfully. As a result, groups of scholars in particular disciplines can articulate the
            specific goals and methods which characterize their work, and the differences which distinguish them from others working in related
            fields. Instead of mutually unintelligible approaches, different projects can produce results whose differences result from real
            disagreements rather than simple random divergence. </p>
        <p/>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="IntroEpigraphers-epidoc">
        <head>The EpiDoc Customization: TEI for Epigraphers</head>
        <p>Within this framework, the <ref target="http://epidoc.sf.net">EpiDoc community</ref> has
            been working, since 2000, to develop a custom version of the TEI Guidelines to support
            the particular needs of epigraphers. The idea was launched by <ref target="http://www.unc.edu/~thomase/">Tom Elliott</ref>, an ancient historian at the
            University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; the aim is both to make the fullest
            possible use of the work that has already been done, and also to ensure that texts which
            happen to be inscribed are handled in a manner consistent with that used for other
            texts, and not distanced from them. The EpiDoc customization removes irrelevant elements
            from the main body of the TEI, and it adds provisions for the specific kinds of
            transcription, analysis, description, and classification that are essential for
            epigraphic work. The result is a simple yet powerful language which can be used to mark
            all of the significant features of inscriptions and also represent the accompanying
            information about the epigraphic object itself.</p>
        <p>To accompany the EpiDoc encoding language, the EpiDoc community has also produced a set
            of <ref target="guidelines.xml">encoding guidelines</ref> and <ref target="epidev.xml">software
            tools</ref>, as well as <ref target="http://epidocumentation.pbwiki.com">documentation</ref> which
            describes how to use the encoding language, the tools, and the other elements of the
            EpiDoc method. The goal is to establish a framework that is easy to learn and use, even
            for scholars with no technical background or support. This may sound improbable, but the
            enterprise is of the same order as learning to mark-up a standard epigraphic text, with
            the existing series of sigla.</p>
        <p>The group has worked to develop expressions for all the agreed epigraphic conventions.
            They have expanded this guidance to address the various fields which may be presented in
            an epigraphic publication, including: <list>
                <item>
                    <ref target="taggingtext.xml">the edition of the epigraphic text itself</ref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <ref target="describing.xml">descriptions of the text, support and context</ref>
                </item>
                <item><ref target="translation.xml">a translation of the text</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="commentary.xml">a scholarly commentary</ref> related to the text and its unique problems and items
                    of interest</item>
                <item><ref target="history.xml">a history of the discovery, documentation, and interpretation of the text</ref>
                    leading to its present publication</item>
                <item><ref target="bibliographicreferences.xml">a bibliography</ref> relevant to this text (xref)</item>
            </list> See further: <ref target="documentstructure.xml">Document Structure</ref>. </p>
        <p>Further areas under active exploration include developing interoperability. A software tool for converting texts in normal epigraphic
            markup into EpiDoc XML has already been developed (the so-called <ref target="chetc.xml">Chapel Hill Electronic Text Converter
            (CHETC)</ref>). Other areas involve the use of authoritative lexica. For example, the Inscriptions of Aphrodisias project is working
            closely with the <ref target="http://www.lgpn.ox.ac.uk/">Lexicon of Greek Personal Names</ref>, to ensure full coverage and consistent
            usage. </p>
        <p>The work, led by Dr. Elliott, has been undertaken by various individual scholars working in close collaboration, and in regular contact
            with the wider profession. They have drawn on the experience of an established EpiDoc project, the <ref target="http://vindolanda.csad.ox.ac.uk/exhibition/">Vindolanda Tablets on line</ref>, and two current projects: the <ref target="http://dev.stg.brown.edu/projects/USEpigraphy/">US Epigraphy Project (USEP)</ref> (supported by Brown, Princeton and Rutgers
            Universities), and the <ref target="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk">Inscriptions of Aphrodisias Project (InsAph)</ref> (supported by the <ref target="http://www.ahrc.ac.uk">Arts and Humanities Research Council</ref>). The generous support of the AHRC allowed for the <ref target="sprintsandstorm.xml">intensive workshop in March 2006</ref> where these guidelines were refined. </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="IntroEpigraphers-responsibility" type="gl-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Charlotte Roueché</name>
                <name/></respStmt>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Julia Flanders</name>
                <name/></respStmt>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>coerced from TEI-Lite and various reformatting edits</resp>
                    <name>Tom Elliott</name>
                <name/></respStmt>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
