<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE div SYSTEM "../dtd/tei-epidoc.dtd" >
<!-- Start CVS information: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: /cvsroot/epidoc/guidelines/src/documentstructureintro.xml,v 1.9 2006/04/27 15:47:40 paregorios Exp $ -->
<!-- End CVS information: do not remove -->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" id="documentstructureintro" lang="en">
    <head>Introduction to EpiDoc Document Structure</head>
    <div type="gl-example" id="example1">
        <head>Example 1</head>
        <ab><tag>TEI.2</tag><lb /> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>teiHeader</tag> ...
            <tag>/teiHeader</tag><lb /> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>text</tag> ... <tag>/text</tag><lb />
        <tag>/TEI.2</tag></ab>
    </div>
    <div id="basicdocumentstructure">
        <head>Basic document structure</head>
        <p>The basic document structure recommended by EpiDoc follows exactly that laid out for
            TEI.2. There are two main sections of the document, both of which are required: the
                <tag>teiHeader</tag> and the <tag>text</tag>. The <tag>teiHeader</tag> is
            essentially the title page and descriptive catalog record for the electronic version of
            the text, providing information about the source of the text, the way it is digitally
            represented and any revisions it has undergone. The <tag>text</tag> element, on the
            other hand, embodies the structure and content of the text itself, including
            introduction, textual edition, translation, critical apparatus, commentary, notes and
            the like. The basic, top-level structure of any such TEI document would look like that
            sketched in <ref target="example1">Example 1</ref>. </p>
        <p>This simple representation of the top-level tagging hides the structural complexity and
            semantic power that can be achieved with TEI. Within each of the two major elements, TEI
            permits (and sometimes requires) the use of a wide range of other elements. Some of
            these elements have very precise rules governing their use. Others permit adaptation to
            meet the needs of particular projects or types of textual materials. </p>
    </div>
    <div id="example2" type="gl-example">
        <head>Example 2: Elements within the <tag>teiHeader</tag></head>
        <ab><tag>TEI.2</tag><lb /> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>teiHeader</tag><lb />
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>fileDesc</tag> ...
        <tag>/fileDesc</tag><lb /> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>encodingDesc</tag>
        ... <tag>/encodingDesc</tag><lb />
        &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>profileDesc</tag> ...
        <tag>/profileDesc</tag><lb />
        &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>revisionDesc</tag> ...
        <tag>/revisionDesc</tag><lb /> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>/teiHeader</tag><lb />
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tag>text</tag> ... <tag>/text</tag><lb />
        <tag>/TEI.2</tag></ab>
    </div>
    <div>
        <head>The <tag>teiHeader</tag></head>
        <p>For example, the <tag>teiHeader</tag> (see <ref target="example2">Example 2</ref>) has a
            very explicit content model, requiring the presence of certain subordinate elements in a
            particular order. It contains the following: </p>
        <list>
            <item><tag>fileDesc</tag>, which provides a full bibliographical description of the
                computer file itself </item>
            <item><tag>encodingDesc</tag>, which describes the relationship between an electronic
                text and its source(s) </item>
            <item><tag>profileDesc</tag> (or 'text profile'), containing classificatory and
                contextual information about the text, such as its subject matter, the situation in
                which it was produced, the individuals described by or participating in producing
                it, and so forth. </item>
            <item><tag>revisionDesc</tag> (or 'revision history'), which allows the encoder to
                provide a history of changes made during the development of the electronic text
            </item>
        </list>
        <p>The use of each of these elements in encoding epigraphic editions (each with its own
            specific content model) is discussed below. In general, see TEI, <xref
                href="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/HD.html">Section 5: The TEI Header for more
            details</xref>. </p>
    </div>
    <div id="example3" type="gl-example">
        <head>Example 3: Outline of EpiDoc usage</head>
        <p>To be completed</p>
        </div>
   <div>
       <head>The <tag>text</tag> element and its subordinate <tag>div</tag>s</head>
       <p>When compared with the <tag>teiHeader</tag>, the top-level <tag>text</tag> element has a more
        flexible content model, as do many of its subordinate elements. This flexibility is
        necessary to accomodate the wide range of textual materials that might require digitization. <ref target="example3">Example 3</ref> provides an abbreviated EpiDoc representation of a boundary marker for an imperial estate in North Africa.</p>
    <p>Within the <tag>text</tag> element of <ref target="example3">Example 3</ref>, one finds the mandatory TEI <tag>body</tag>
        element. TEI provides that this element can be subdivided further into any number of logical
        divisions using the <tag>div</tag> element. TEI specifies the use of the <tag>div</tag>
        element for the hierarchical grouping of divisions and subdivisions within a text. Depending
        on the genre of the text, these 'groups' can have different common names, such as 'chapter'
        in a novel, 'scene' in a play, or 'book' in an ancient literary work. Rather than elaborate
        differently named elements for each and every possible such grouping, TEI employs the
        generic <tag>div</tag> element for all such divisions. The TEI specification for the
            <tag>div</tag> element provides a standard attribute named <att>type</att>. This
        attribute is used to categorize these <tag>div</tag> elements independently of their
        hierarchical relationships using a set of attribute values appropriate to the genre and
        audience of the text. In this way, the nesting of <tag>div</tag> elements can be used to
        indicate the hierarchical relationship between a chapter and a subsection, while the
            <att>type</att> attribute can be used simultaneously to indicate the semantic difference
        between a chapter and an appendix. Note: <ref target="example3">Example 3</ref> does not 'nest' its <tag>div</tag>
        elements, so there are not any significant hierarchical relationships between divisions of
        this particular text. But there are significant semantic differences, as indicated by the
        use of the <att>type</att> attribute. </p>
    <p>In this example, the <att>type</att> attribute of the <tag>div</tag> element is used to
        distinguish between six different types of divisions: </p>
    <p>a description of the text and/or monument; </p>
    <p>the edition of the epigraphic text itself; </p>
    <p>a translation of that text; </p>
    <p>a scholarly commentary related to the text and its unique problems and items of interest; </p>
    <p>a history of the discovery, documentation, and interpretation of the text leading to its
        present publication; and </p>
    <p>a bibliography relevent to this text. </p>
    <p>These attribute values (and two more: metadata and diplomatic) have been introduced as part
        of the EpiDoc standard (see Section 5.5: EpiDoc divisions (tei:div) of the text element
        (tei:text) for the formal definition of the <tag>div/</tag> element and its attributes). TEI
        places no limits or requirements on the use of the <att>type</att> attribute; it merely
        makes <att>type</att> available "to provide a name or description for the division." We have
        deliberately kept the number of EpiDoc values for <att>type</att> small to ensure the
        greatest possible degree of smooth interchange between EpiDoc-conformant projects. </p>
    <p>EpiDoc exploits the flexibility and specificity of the <tag>div/</tag> element and its
            <att>type</att> attribute to distinguish between the various components commonly found
        in the scholarly presentation of epigraphic texts. Compare the conventional print
        representation of ALA 2 (Example 4) with the XML version in Example 3. Although styles and
        presentation differ from one scholarly epigraphic publication to the next, at a basic level,
        this example is representative of the historiographic genre. Typographic cues are generally
        used to alert the reader to a change in the character of information being presented for
        each text, but the exact nature of such changes is often simply implied. We assume that our
        reader understands the conventions of epigraphic publication. In the XML counterpart, the
        semantic differences between each division are made explicit using standard values for the
            <att>type</att> attribute. </p>
    <p>These semantic distinctions, encoded into a digital text from its creation, facilitate a
        number of important possibilities when the time comes to prepare the text for presentation
        to a user or incorporate it into another publication or project. Standard XML software can
        use combinations of element and attribute values to select, compare, combine and reformat
        semantically discrete portions of documents in complex ways, providing the semantic
        distinctions have been explicitly encoded in a standard manner. The typed divisions of TEI,
        when categorized according to a generally-agreed and epigraphically relevant scheme,
        constitute such a standard. </p>
    <p>Divisions with the same type attribute value can be repeated as necessary, and further
        semantic distinctions between them drawn at the editor's discretion using the standard TEI
        attribute <att>n</att>. These arrangements permit extensive, project-specific flexibility in
        searching, formatting and reusing documents. There are no EpiDoc-mandated values for n, but
        projects are encouraged to develop standard usage and publish documentation thereof as part
        of their dataset. The EPAPP project has developed such a system of attribute values, as
        demonstrated by the text in Example 5. The EPAPP system of values for n on the
        <tag>div</tag> element has been adopted by these guidelines as a recommendation for projects
        which find it helpful. </p></div>
        <div id="documentstructureintro-responsibility" type="gl-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>to be added</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
    <div id="documentstructureintro-cvs" type="gl-cvs">
        <head><abbr expan="Concurrent Versioning System">CVS</abbr> Information</head>
        <p id="documentstructureintro-cvs-revision-number">Revision number: <seg n="cvs-revision-number"
            >$Revision: 1.9 $</seg></p>
        <p id="documentstructureintro-cvs-revision-name">Revision name (if any): <seg n="cvs-revision-name"
            >$Name: r-5 $</seg></p>
        <p id="documentstructureintro-cvs-revision-date">Revision date: <seg n="cvs-revision-date"
            >$Date: 2006/04/27 15:47:40 $</seg></p>
        <p id="documentstructureintro-cvs-revision-author">Revision committed by: <seg n="cvs-revision-author"
            >$Author: paregorios $</seg></p>
    </div>
</div>
