<?xml version = "1.0" encoding = "UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://www.unc.edu/awmc/epidoc/speed/documents/speedtei.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY ClaudianBS 'bs'>
  <!ENTITY ClaudianPS 'ps'>
  <!ENTITY ClaudianV 'v'>
  <!ENTITY ClaudianY 'y'>
]>
<TEI.2 id="CHANGEME_1">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
        <!-- users should change this title to something more appropriate for their text -->
				<title lang="eng">Epigraphic Document Generated with the Chapel Hill Epigraphic Text Converter (CHET-C)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>Documents generated with CHET-C may be used for whatever purpose the user desires, consistent with copyright and other restrictions related to the materials and information that user fed to CHET-C so long as the sourceDesc or publicationDesc contains an acknowledgement of the use of CHET-C in creating the document. That acknowledgement should include the CHET-C authors' names (see sourceDesc for details).</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This file was generated using the Chapel Hill Epigraphic Text Converter (CHET-C), which was written by Tom Elliott, Hugh Cayless and Noel Fiser at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill. CHET-C takes traditional epigraphic texts and converts them to semantic markup in compliance with the TEI and EpiDoc guidelines for text markup in XML. All standard epigraphic editorial sigla and conventions are converted to semantic markup. Neither CHET-C nor its writers know anything about what text was input to the program or where it came from. Information about those matters should be added to the sourceDesc by the user of CHET-C.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <creation>
        <date value="2002-05-14">14 May 2002</date> in <name type="geographic">CHANGEME_3</name>
      </creation>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="ara">Arabic</language>
        <language id="cat">Catalan</language>
        <language id="dut">Dutch</language>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
        <language id="fre">French</language>
        <language id="ger">German</language>
        <language id="grc">Greek, Ancient</language>
        <language id="gre">Greek, Modern</language>
        <language id="ita">Italian</language>
        <language id="lat">Latin</language>
        <language id="peo">Persian, Old</language>
        <language id="rus">Russian</language>
        <language id="spa">Spanish</language>
        <language id="tur">Turkish</language>
        <language id="ukr">Ukrainian</language>
      </langUsage>
      <handList>
        <!-- if only one hand appears in this document, then the second hand tag should be deleted -->
        <!-- if more than two hands appear in this document, then additional hand tags should be added -->
        <hand id="hand1" first="yes"/>
        <hand id="hand2" first="no"/>
      </handList>
    </profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<p/>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>