<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Copyright (C) 2000-2006 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!DOCTYPE div SYSTEM "../dtd/tei-epidoc.dtd">
<!-- Start CVS information: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: /data/epidoc/cvs/epidoc-cvsbackup/guidelines/src/conformance.xml,v 1.3 2006-12-08 13:59:19 paregorios Exp $ -->
<!-- End CVS information: do not remove -->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="conformance" lang="en" rend="integral">
   <head>Conformance and Interoperability: What it means to <soCalled>be</soCalled> EpiDoc</head>
    <p>This section of the <bibl><title level="m">Guidelines</title></bibl> attempts to answer the following questions:</p>
    <list type="unordered">
        <item>What are the distinctive and consistent features that make it possible to label a
            digital encoding project as <soCalled>an EpiDoc project</soCalled>?</item>
        <item>What are the minimum recommendations or requirements of the EpiDoc Guidelines?</item>
        <item>How can one verify that a file or a project is EpiDoc-compliant?</item>
        <item>How can one ensure that one&apos;s EpiDoc files are ready for reliable interchange
            with other projects, as well as conversion using standard stylesheets and other tools?</item>
        <item>What is the relationship of EpiDoc to the Leiden Conventions?</item>
        <item>What is the relationship of EpiDoc to the Information Technology Initiative of AIEGL,
            the International Association for Greek and Latin Epigraphy, and its Electronic Archive
            of Greek and Latin Epigraphy (EAGLE)?</item>
    </list>
    <div id="conformance-levels">
        <head>Conformance Levels</head>
        <p>The <xref href="guidelines.xml">EpiDoc Guidelines</xref> provide examples and advice for
            a wide range of encoding needs, and can facilitate the work of both restrospective and
            born-digital projects. Moreover, these <bibl><title level="m">Guidelines</title></bibl> 
            can be used across the full spectrum of complexity, from the handling of
            transcribed texts alone (for example, inside other XML schemata or database text fields)
            to extensive, complete, 100%-EpiDoc corpora. Accordingly, the EpiDoc Community
            recognizes the following levels of conformance. Projects that can demonstrate the
            conformance of their product with one or both of the following levels may be listed as
            an <soCalled>EpiDoc Project</soCalled> on the <xref href="http://epidoc.sourceforge.net"
                >EpiDoc Website</xref>.</p>
        <div id="conformance-leiden">
            <head>Leiden-conformant EpiDoc</head>
            <p>Leiden-conformance is the most basic, and most essential, class of EpiDoc markup. It
                addresses itself only to the process of textual transcription, and — in
                this regard — we recognize only those editorial distinctions regularly
                employed by editors following the Leiden Conventions and their major emendations
                (plus standard critical apparatus). Because EpiDoc encodes the semantics of the
                editorial process, specific sigla (e.g., square brackets, subscript dots,
                parentheses) cannot be used in the text. Rather, the XML encodings labeled, in these 
                <bibl><title level="m" type="main">Guidelines</title></bibl>, as <soCalled>required</soCalled> 
                for Leiden-conformant EpiDoc must be
                applied consistently and completely throughout all transcribed texts in a given
                digital publication if it is to be considered <soCalled>Leiden-conformant
                    EpiDoc</soCalled>. Note that most if not all of the Leiden-sigla-to-EpiDoc-markup transformation 
                can be accomplished automatically by tools such as <xref href="chetc.xml">CHET-C</xref>.
                Moreover, the relevant transcribed text must validate against an appropriate
                released version of the EpiDoc DTD or schema. An XML fragment may be
                considered a valid EpiDoc file if it is properly handled.</p>
            <p>For further details, please see the list of <xref href="conformance-leiden-list.xml">Mandatory Considerations for Leiden Conformance</xref>.</p>
            
        </div>
        <div id="conformance-aiegl">
            <head>EAGLE-conformant EpiDoc</head>
            <p>EAGLE-conformant EpiDoc publications are, by definition, Leiden-conformant EpiDoc publications.
            Above and beyond full conformance with EpiDoc specifications for basic text transcription, 
            AIEGL-conformant EpiDoc publications also must embody specific structures, components and 
            metadata elements necessary to facilitate consistent, automatic incorporation of their content
            into the appropriate subsystem of the federated epigraphic database system sponsored by
            the International Association of Greek and Latin Epigraphy: <xref href="http://www.eagle-eagle.it">The Electronic Archive of Greek and 
                Latin Epigraphy (EAGLE)</xref>. The provisions for EAGLE
            conformance go well beyond the semantics of transcription to incorporate
            description, classification and certain base elements of analysis. In addition to the 
                provisions of <ref target="conformance-leiden">Leiden-conformant EpiDoc</ref>, the XML encodings 
                labeled, in these <bibl><title level="m" type="main">Guidelines</title></bibl>, as 
                <soCalled>required</soCalled> for EAGLE-conformant EpiDoc must be
                applied consistently and completely throughout the work if it is to be considered 
                <soCalled>EAGLE-conformant EpiDoc</soCalled>. Moreover, the entire epigraphic presentation must 
                validate against an appropriate
            released version of the EpiDoc DTD or schema; note that an XML fragment may be considered a valid EpiDoc 
                file if it is properly handled.</p>
            <p>For further details, please see the list of <xref href="conformance-aiegl-list.xml">Mandatory Considerations 
                for EAGLE Conformance</xref>.</p>
        </div>
        <div id="conformance-other">
            <head>Other EpiDoc Recommendations</head>
            <p>These Guidelines include some provisions that have been designated neither as Leiden-conforming
            nor as EAGLE-conforming. As such, the following subsections describe optional encoding 
            strategies. Some are experimental or developmental. Others are advanced capabilities that
            are not required by all projects.</p>
        </div>
        
    </div>
    
    <div id="conformance-responsibility" type="gl-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Tom Elliott</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
    <div id="conformance-cvs" type="gl-cvs">
        <head><abbr expan="Concurrent Versioning System">CVS</abbr> Information</head>
        <p id="conformance-cvs-revision-number">Revision number: <seg n="cvs-revision-number">$Revision$</seg></p>
        <p id="conformance-cvs-revision-name">Revision name (if any): <seg n="cvs-revision-name">$Name: not supported by cvs2svn $</seg></p>
        <p id="conformance-cvs-revision-date">Revision date: <seg n="cvs-revision-date">$Date$</seg></p>
        <p id="conformance-cvs-revision-author">Revision committed by: <seg n="cvs-revision-author">$Author$</seg></p>
    </div>
</div>
