<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE div SYSTEM "../dtd/tei-epidoc.dtd">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" id="dates" lang="en">
    <head>Dates</head>
    <p>Dates may be identified in the ancient text (consular years, olympiads, etc.), or in editorial discussion. The date element contains a date in any format. There are basically three contexts in which an expression might be tagged as a date in an EpiDoc file:</p>
    <list type="unordered">
        <item>a regular date expression in a bibliographical citation or editorial discussion;</item>
        <item>any kind of date expression in the original text of an inscription;</item>
        <item>the editor's dating of an inscription or monument, either by a specific date or a span of years or centuries.</item>
    </list>
    <p>(Note: A year or regular date in the Gregorian calendar may simply be tagged as a <tag>date</tag> with no further information required from attribute values. If the date or span of dates is expressed in prose, in ancient terms, or in a different calendar, further information may be given using the following attributes.)</p>
    <p>There are two groups of attributes which add information to the date element. The attributes 'value' and 'precision' express a single date, exactly or approximately, whereas 'notBefore', 'notAfter', and 'exact' define a span of possible dates within which the date in question may be located.</p>
    <list type="unordered">
        <item>value: in an ancient date expression this attribute may indicate the regularised date in the Julian calendar; if the date is already numerical and unproblematic, it may be ommitted;</item>
        <item>precision: the level of accuracy to be assigned to "value", e.g. "approx" or "exact";</item>
    </list>
    <ab>versus:</ab>
    <list type="unordered">
        <item>notBefore: beginning of a span of possible dates;</item>
        <item>notAfter: end of span of possible dates;</item>
        <item>exact: refers to the previous two attributes; values include 'notBefore', 'notAfter', 'both' and 'none'.</item>
    </list>
    <p>Date expressions should be given in the form recommended by ISO 8601:2000, i.e. 'yyyy-mm-dd'. This means that years below 1000 (either BCE or CE) need leading zeroes to make them up to four digits. (See examples below.) When a date is not known to the very day the shortened forms 'yyyy-mm' and 'yyyy' may be used. Dates BCE should be indicated by the placement of a minus sign (hyphen) before the date expression. (Unlike ISO 8601:2000 we do not assume the existance of a year zero in the Gregorian calendar, so 44 BCE is "-0044" not "-0043".)</p>
    <p>There is also an additional attribute 'calendar', which may be used to express the non-regular dating system in the case of dates in the original text. Example values include: 'Attic', 'A.U.C.', 'Julian', Amphictionic, Macedonian, etc.</p>
    <p>(Note: the difference between a single date <hi rend="strong">within</hi> a span of possibilities (marked by the notBefore and notAfter attributes of <tag>date</tag>, as above) and an expression indicating a time period (such as the reign of an emperor). For the latter EpiDoc recommends the use of <tag>dateRange</tag>, as documented in the TEI Guidelines.)</p>
    <div id="dates-epidoc">
        <head>EpiDoc encodings</head>
        <div id="dates-epidoc-in-description">
            <head>Inscription/monument dates in <tag>div type="description"</tag></head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item><tag>date notBefore="-0399" notAfter="-0398" exact="both"</tag>399/8 BCE<tag>/date</tag></item>
                <item><tag>date notBefore="0201" notAfter="0225" exact="none"</tag>First quarter third century CE<tag>/date</tag></item>
                <item><tag>date notBefore="14" notAfter="39" exact="notBefore"</tag>Within a quarter century of the death of Augustus<tag>/date</tag></item>
                <item><tag>date value="-0044-03-15" precision="exact"</tag>the Ides of March 44<tag>/date</tag> (Note the use of Julian calendar!)</item>
                <item><tag>date value="0523-02-14" precision="exact"</tag>ἰνδικτίωνος α´ μηνὸς β´, ιδ´, ἡμέρα τρίτη<tag>/date</tag></item>
            </list>
        </div>
        <div id="dates-epidoc-elsewhere">
            <head>Dates elsewhere, bibliography, etc.</head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Roueché (<tag>date</tag>1989<tag>/date</tag>), no. 22</item>
            </list>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div id="dates-edition" lang="lat">
        <head lang="en">EpiDoc appearance with standard XSLT</head>
        <div id="dates-edition-in-description">
            <head lang="en">Inscription/monument dates in <tag>div type="description"</tag></head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                    <date notBefore="-0399" notAfter="-0398" exact="both">399/8 BCE</date>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <date notBefore="0201" notAfter="0225" exact="none">First quarter third century CE</date>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <date notBefore="14" notAfter="39" exact="notBefore">Within a quarter century of the death of Augustus</date>
                </item>
                <item><date value="-0044-03-15" precision="exact">the Ides of March 44</date> (Note the use of Julian calendar!)</item>
                <item>
                    <date value="0523-02-14" precision="exact">ἰνδικτίωνος α´ μηνὸς β´, ιδ´, ἡμέρα τρίτη</date>
                </item>
            </list>
        </div>
        <div id="dates-edition-elsewhere">
            <head lang="en">Dates elsewhere, bibliography, etc.</head>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Roueché (<date>1989</date>), no. 22</item>
            </list>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div id="tei-p4links">
        <head>TEI P4 links</head>
        <list>
            <item>
                <xref href="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/ref-DATE.html">
                    <tag>date</tag>
                </xref>
            </item>
            <item>
                <xref href="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/CO.html#CONADA">6.4.4. Dates and Times</xref>
            </item>
            <item>
                <xref href="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/ND.html#NDDATE">20.4 Dates and Time</xref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
    <div id="vestiges-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Gabriel Bodard</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>re-encoded from xwiki to TEI-ish</resp>
                    <name>Tom Elliott</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
