<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div SYSTEM "../dtd/tei-epidoc.dtd">
<!-- Start CVS information: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: /data/epidoc/cvs/epidoc-cvsbackup/guidelines/src/introduction.xml,v 1.6 2006-04-18 19:52:26 paregorios Exp $ -->
<!-- End CVS information: do not remove -->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" id="introduction" lang="en">
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <div id="introduction-general">
        <head>The EpiDoc Guidelines</head>
        <p>The EpiDoc Guidelines were created to describe, document and explain the use of the
            TEI-based EpiDoc encoding scheme, which provides for the realization of electronic
            epigraphic editions, corpora and similar materials in XML. The guidelines also provide
            directions and documentation for epigraphists and software developers who are engaged in
            creating or refining EpiDoc software tools, and even the Guidelines themselves.</p>
        <p>The EpiDoc Guidelines embody more than prose and encoding examples for direct examination
            by human readers. They also contain carefully encoded data strings that are picked up
            and used by core EpiDoc software tools. As a result, the Guidelines function as the lone
            source from which the various converting and formatting mechanisms developed by the
            EpiDoc community draw the settings that specify their behavior, in particular with
            regard to mappings between traditional sigla for epigraphic transcription and the
            TEI/XML encodings specified by EpiDoc. Self-test mechanisms for the Guidelines, designed
            and implemented by Hugh Cayless during the <xref href="sprintsandstorm.xml">EpiDoc
                Sandstorm Development Sprint</xref> in London (March 2006), ensure that the
            behaviors of these tools remain reliably synchonized with each other, and with the
            encoding guidance and explanation the Guidelines provide to human readers.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="introduction-bg">
        <head>Background and Rationale</head>
        <p>One of the great achievements of the 1931 Leiden meeting was the establishment of a set
            of common notational practices for epigraphic and papyrological transcription. In the
            21st century, the next hurdle/challenge to be met is of the same sort: to migrate these
            practices into the digital arena and extend them in a way that takes advantage of the
            functional opportunities offered by the new medium. The goal of the EpiDoc consortium is
            to do just this (see further: <xref href="IntroEpigraphers.xml">Introduction for
                Epigraphers</xref>). The toolkit it provides includes a TEI-conformant markup
            language, a set of XML tools to assist in transcription and publication (see <xref
                href="epidev.xml">EpiDoc Development</xref>, and full documentation of how to use
            both. </p>
        <p>The EpiDoc toolkit is useful in a number of ways. It can help make basic activities such
            as transcription and sharing of documents much easier. For projects using standard XML
            tools and TEI/EpiDoc markup, sharing documents between projects becomes as simple as
            telling the software where to find the new file. For projects engaged in converting
            materials from Leiden notation to XML, manual conversion of data and re-entering of
            texts will become a thing of the past; the EpiDoc tools can convert directly from Leiden
            notation to EpiDoc markup without manual intervention. </p>
        <p>But beyond the tremendous practical benefits to be realized from automated conversion and
            project-to-project data sharing, individual projects can gain other advantages from
            adopting EpiDoc techniques. One of the most significant is the ability to produce much
            more powerful user interfaces, which can be adapted easily to the needs of different
            user groups. One can imagine a website in which customizable user preferences dictate
            whether standard glosses for the various division types are presented to or hidden from
            the user (i.e., a helpful, student-oriented interface vs. a compact, streamlined view
            for scholars). Printed output in a variety of formats is also easy to produce from the
            EpiDoc-encoded source. Another important advantage is the ability to provide more
            nuanced searching, using the EpiDoc markup to identify specific search contexts and
            terms. Users can search for date ranges found only in 'description' divisions, for Latin
            abbreviations found only in 'edition' divisions, or for English words appearing only in
            'translation' divisions. In assembling a large database of inscriptions, an automated
            process could easily be put to the task of reading all the entries from the
            'bibliography' divisions of hundreds of individual texts prepared by a number of
            different projects, then collating the citations into a single master bibliography file
            for the entire database (for the major divisions of an EpiDoc document, see <xref
                href="documentstructure.xml">Document Structure</xref>).</p>
    </div>
    <div id="introduction-responsibility" type="gl-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Tom Elliott</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Julia Flanders</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Charlotte Roueché</name>
                </respStmt>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
    <div id="introduction-cvs" type="gl-cvs">
        <head><abbr expan="Concurrent Versioning System">CVS</abbr> Information</head>
        <p id="introduction-cvs-revision-number">Revision number: <seg n="cvs-revision-number"
                >$Revision: 1.6 $</seg></p>
        <p id="introduction-cvs-revision-name">Revision name (if any): <seg n="cvs-revision-name"
                >$Name: not supported by cvs2svn $</seg></p>
        <p id="introduction-cvs-revision-date">Revision date: <seg n="cvs-revision-date">$Date:
                2006/03/23 18:27:47 $</seg></p>
        <p id="introduction-cvs-revision-author">Revision committed by: <seg n="cvs-revision-author"
                >$Author: paregorios $</seg></p>
    </div>
</div>
