<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Copyright (C) 2000-2006 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="intro-intro" xml:lang="en">
    <head>General Introduction to the EpiDoc Guidelines</head>

    <p>EpiDoc is a loose collaborative of projects and scholars working with ancient source
        documents in <term target="#tei">Text Encoding Initiative</term> (TEI) <term target="#xml"
            >XML</term>, and devising recommendations, tools, and good practice for the <term
            target="#encoding">encoding</term>, processing and publishing of such texts. The EpiDoc
        Guidelines describe and document how to encode the various features of epigraphic and
        papyrological documents, based on the core principles of the disciplines (e.g. the Leiden
        Conventions for transcriptional features, data structures such as <term target="#eagle"
            >EAGLE</term> and others for descriptive and historical elements). The Guidelines should
        be used in conjunction with the EpiDoc schema, against which documents marked up according
        to these principles should validate, and the EpiDoc Example <term target="#xslt"
        >XSLT</term>, which attempts to provide a basic rendering for each feature described.</p>

    <p>The EpiDoc Guidelines cannot attempt to give full explanation of how to set up an EpiDoc
        project, generate a website, build search tools, or other technical or collaborative tasks
        required for the publication of encoded texts online. No more are the Guidelines a full
        introduction to EpiDoc, or to epigraphy or papyrology; they are exclusively a guide to the
        XML encoding of the features of an ancient documentary text edition that are most often
        needed in epigraphic and similar scholarship.</p>

    <p>The EpiDoc Guidelines are intended to complement the <term target="#leiden">Leiden
            Conventions</term> that have been in use in epigraphy and papyrology for over 80 years
        and are well understood in the discipline. The Guidelines assume that Leiden is an adequate
        basis for the intellectual distinctions recorded in a transcription of an ancient text, and
        base the recommendations and examples upon these distinctions. It is often possible for TEI
        to record distinctions that are finer or deeper than Leiden, and some such possibilities are
        described herein, but these Guidelines do not recommend replacing standard epigraphic or
        papyrological practice with such new principles. Likewise, the default behaviour of the
        EpiDoc Example XSLT is to produce Leiden rendering of EpiDoc-encoded texts.</p>

    <p>Although there is no single convention for the structure of an epigraphic or papyrological
        edition, in the way that Leiden sets out the critical marks for the transcribed text, the
        EpiDoc Guidelines (and <term target="#xslt">XSLT</term>) take a similar approach to data
        structures such as <term target="#eagle">EAGLE</term>, <term target="#petrae">PETRAE</term>
        or <term target="#apis">APIS</term>: namely that the discipline already has rigorous models
        of good practice in structuring editions, we merely recommend the encoding of the same
        distinctions to which scholars are accustomed in TEI XML.</p>

    <p>The Guidelines produced and recommended by the EpiDoc community represent a subset of and
        refinement to the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">TEI
            Guidelines</ref>, which recommend the XML encoding of a wide range of literary and
        historical texts and linguistic corpora. Just as EpiDoc is a specialization of the TEI for
        ancient documents and objects, recommending only those elements, attributes and objects of
        value for this specific sub-community, the EpiDoc Guidelines are intended to supplement (and
        by no means replace) the TEI Guidelines. Especially the reference and technical sections of
        the TEI remain an invaluable resource for users of EpiDoc, who will often find lists of
        elements, explanations of attribute values or data types, examples of usage in a wide range
        of contexts and extensive prose descriptions of markup features useful. The EpiDoc
        Guidelines recommend a rather restricted set of TEI elements, content models, attributes and
        values, such that an EpiDoc file is always also a valid TEI file, but not every TEI file is
        valid EpiDoc. Where the EpiDoc Guidelines are more restrictive than the TEI, the former
        should be considered to supercede the latter; but where the TEI goes into more detail, or
        offers a more useful range of examples, it should of course be consulted and considered the
        canonical source for all EpiDoc usage.</p>

    <p>There are several pathways into the individual pages that make up the body of the EpiDoc
        Guidelines.</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
        <item>Three main tables of contents collect together all of these pages under the
            categories: <hi rend="bold">Transcription</hi> (those features relating to the content,
            appearance, restoration and basic interpretation of the text itself); <hi rend="bold"
                >Supporting Data</hi> (including the description of the object or manuscript, the
            history of the object and its discovery, bibliographical and other editorial
            information); and <hi rend="bold">Vocabulary and Indexing</hi> (terms and features
            tagged in the text for purpose of vocabulary control or indexing, searching and
            faceting).</item>
        <item>Several sections offer organized and selected lists of guidance pages according to the
            categories generally followed by users of specialized communities (for example, the
            epigraphic transcription guidelines of <term target="#krummreypanciera"
                >Krummrey-Panciera</term>; the papyrological features as recorded by the <term
                target="#apis">APIS</term> database). These sections are under construction, and
            should be considered informational rather than normative. Suggestions of new sections of
            this kind are welcome.</item>
        <item>Finally the Guidelines contain supporting appendices, such as the glossary of
            technical and specialized terms, and a bibliography of epigraphic and papyrological
            authorities, example EpiDoc corpora, and on digital publication of ancient texts
            generally. An index to the guidelines by TEI elements mentioned allows readers to find
            all epigraphic features in which a given element is part of the recommended
            usage.</item>
    </list>

    <p>Individual pages in the Guidelines are organised by epigraphic or papyrological concept,
        rather than by TEI element name. So, for instance, all pages involving abbreviations are
        grouped together, regardless of what TEI elements are specified. Each Guidelines page has a
        regular structure: first, a brief explanation of the title of a page (e.g., for the page
        entitled ‘Uninterpreted Characters’, there is an explanation “Clear but incomprehensible
        letters”). The relevant TEI element (or elements) are displayed in a box underneath,
        including a link to the TEI Guidelines page for that element. There then follows a prose
        explanation of the EpiDoc recommendations for the use of those TEI elements, including
        details of relevant attributes and values.</p>

    <p>Below this explanation there are usually a few examples of this usage in context. Especially
        in the case of transcriptional features, the Guidelines will list conventional renderings of
        the issue in question according to common epigraphic or papyrological transcription
        guidelines, such as <term target="#krummreypanciera">Krummrey-Panciera</term> and the <term
            target="#ddb">Duke Databank</term>.</p>

    <p>The XML examples show the recommended markup for the various types of each transcriptional
        feature, e. g. different cases of expansion of an abbreviation which includes a symbol. The
        examples list several markup options also depending on the level of detail desired. Below
        the examples there is a series of renderings (or a different rendering after each example)
        which represent the several outputs available in the example EpiDoc P5 stylesheets. The
        default output is following the <term target="#krummreypanciera">Krummrey-Panciera</term>
        conventions. The others include the SEG style, the London style and the DDbDP style. Below
        each example there is a reference pointing to its source. Most of the examples are taken
        from the <term target="#insaph">Inscriptions of Aphrodisias</term>, the <term target="#irt"
            >Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</term> and the <term target="#ddb">Duke Databank of
            Documentary Papyri</term>. </p>

    <p>These guidelines are in essence a reference source. For more in-depth training or support,
        other resources might be available. Member of the EpiDoc community run occasional training
        schools, sometimes funded by major projects (such as several workshops run during the
        Inscriptions of Aphrodisias Project, 2004-2008); more information on these training events
        can be found in the <ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/Training/">EpiDoc
            Wiki</ref>. Those new to EpiDoc and text encoding might also find general training
        sessions on TEI (some listed in <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Current_events"
            >TEI Events list</ref>) useful.</p>

    <p>EpiDoc can be authored and edited using any standard tool for XML (several of which are
        listed at the <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Category:Editing_tools">TEI
            wiki</ref>); basic training in the use of such tools is usually included in both EpiDoc
        and TEI training events, or any XML tutorial. Other tools for publishing, searching and
        otherwise processing EpiDoc and TEI files include the XML transformation languages <ref
            target="http://www.w3schools.com/xsl/xsl_intro.asp">XSLT</ref> and <ref
            target="http://www.w3schools.com/xquery/xquery_intro.asp">XQuery</ref>, and general
        searching platforms such as <ref target="http://lucene.apache.org/solr/">Solr</ref> and TEI
        specific open source tools like <ref target="https://github.com/kcl-ddh/kiln">Kiln</ref> and
        the <ref target="https://github.com/papyri/navigator">Papyrological Navigator</ref>.</p>

    <p>As always, the first port of call for help with any topic not covered by these guidelines
        should be the <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/MarkupList/">Markup
            list</ref>.</p>



    <div xml:id="intro-intro-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Gabriel Bodard</name>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Laura Löser</name>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Simona Stoyanova</name>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Charlotte Tupman</name>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
