<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>
 
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="intro-intro-de" xml:lang="de">
    <head>General Introduction to the EpiDoc Guidelines</head>

    <p>EpiDoc is a loose collaborative of projects and scholars working with ancient source
        documents in <term target="#tei">Text Encoding Initiative</term> (TEI) <term target="#xml"
            >XML</term>, and devising recommendations, tools, and good practice for the digital
            <term target="#encoding">encoding</term>, processing and publishing of such texts.
        EpiDoc's home page on the web may be found at <ref target="http://epidoc.sf.net"
            >http://epidoc.sf.net</ref>.</p>

    <p>The present document (the <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title>) is the on-going product of the
        EpiDoc community's work over several years. It describes how to encode the various features
        of epigraphic and papyrological documents, based on the core principles of scholarly text
        editing (e.g. the so-called <term target="#leiden">Leiden Conventions</term> for
        transcriptional features, and data models such as <term target="#eagle">Electronic Archive of
            Greek and Latin Epigraphy (EAGLE)</term> for descriptive and historical elements). The
            <title>Guidelines</title> should be used in conjunction with the <title><term
                target="#epidoc-schema">EpiDoc Schema</term></title>, against which documents marked
        up according to these principles should validate, and the <title><term
                target="#epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc Example Stylesheets</term></title>, which attempt
        to provide a basic rendering for each feature described.</p>

    <p>The <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title> cannot undertake to give full explanation of how to set up
        an EpiDoc project, generate a website, build search tools, or other technical or
        collaborative tasks required for the publication of encoded texts online. No more are the
            <title>Guidelines</title> a full introduction to epigraphy or papyrology;
        they are exclusively a guide to the XML encoding of the features of an ancient documentary
        text edition that are most often needed in epigraphic and similar scholarship.</p>

    <p>Although there is no single convention for the structure of an epigraphic or papyrological
        edition the
        <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title> (and the <title><term target="epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc
            Stylesheets</term></title>) take an approach that is in accord with the data models employed by
        projects and collaborations like the <term target="#apis">Advanced Papyrological Information
            System (APIS)</term>, <term target="#eagle">EAGLE</term>, and <term target="#petrae"
                ><foreign xml:lang="fr">Programme d’enregistrement, de traitement et de recherche
                    automatique en épigraphie</foreign> (PETRAE)</term>. As the discipline if epigrpaphy in general
        digital epigraphy in particular, 
        already have rigorous models of good practice in structuring editions, we merely recommend the
        encoding in TEI XML of the same data and observations that scholars have already found
        essential or useful in practice.</p>
    
    <p>The <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title> are intended to complement the <term target="#leiden"
            >Leiden Conventions</term> (hereafter "Leiden"), which have been in use in epigraphy and
        papyrology for over 80 years and are understood in many philological and documentary fields.
        The <title>Guidelines</title> assume that Leiden is an adequate basis for the intellectual
        distinctions recorded in an edition of a pre-modern text, and base their recommendations and
        examples upon these distinctions without requiring the specific typographical conventions and
        sigla recommended therein. That is, EpiDoc seeks clearly to record in XML such textual
        interventions as an editor's supplement for characters wholly lost to damage, but does not
        specify that such supplements must be rendered within "square brackets" ("[" and "]") in the
        XML itself or in any downstream output. That said, it is the default behaviour of the
            <title>EpiDoc Example Stylesheets</title> to produce a Leiden rendering of EpiDoc-encoded
        texts. It is often possible for TEI to record distinctions that are finer or deeper than
        Leiden, and some such possibilities are described herein, but these <title>Guidelines</title>
        do not recommend replacing standard epigraphic or papyrological practice with such new
        principles.</p>

    <p>The <title>Guidelines</title> produced and recommended by the EpiDoc community represent a
        subset of and refinement to the <title><ref
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">TEI
                Guidelines</ref></title>, which recommend the XML encoding of a wide range of
        literary and historical texts and linguistic corpora. Just as EpiDoc is a specialization of
        the TEI for ancient documents and objects, recommending only those elements, attributes and
        objects of value for this specific sub-community, the <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title> are
        intended to supplement (and by no means replace) the <title>TEI Guidelines</title>.
        Especially the reference and technical sections of the TEI remain an invaluable resource for
        users of EpiDoc, who will often find lists of elements, explanations of attribute values or
        data types, examples of usage in a wide range of contexts and extensive prose descriptions of
        markup features useful. The <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title> recommend a rather restricted
        set of TEI elements, content models, attributes and values, such that an EpiDoc file is
        always also a valid TEI file, but not every TEI file is valid EpiDoc. Where the <title>EpiDoc
            Guidelines</title> are more restrictive than the TEI, the former should be considered to
        supercede the latter; but where the TEI goes into more detail, or offers a more useful range
        of examples, it should of course be consulted and considered the canonical source for all
        EpiDoc usage.</p>
    
    <div xml:id="structure-de">
        <head>Structure and Features of the <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title></head>

        <p>There are several pathways into the individual pages that make up the body of the
                <title>EpiDoc Guidelines</title>.</p>
        <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Three main tables of contents collect together all of these pages under the
                categories: <ref rend="bold" target="app-alltrans.html">Transcription</ref> (those
                features relating to the content, appearance, restoration and basic interpretation of
                the text itself); <ref rend="bold" target="app-allsupp.html">Supporting Data</ref>
                (including the description of the object or manuscript, the history of the object and
                its discovery, bibliographical and other editorial information); and <ref rend="bold"
                    target="app-allidx.html">Vocabulary and Indexing</ref> (terms and features tagged
                in the text for purpose of vocabulary control or indexing, searching and
                faceting).</item>
            <item><ref target="index.html#special">Several sections</ref> offer organized and
                selected lists of guidance pages according to the categories generally followed by
                users of specialized communities (for example, the epigraphic transcription
                guidelines of <term target="#krummreypanciera">Krummrey-Panciera</term>; the
                papyrological features as recorded by the <term target="#apis">APIS</term> database).
                These sections are under construction, and should be considered informational rather
                than normative. Suggestions of new sections of this kind are welcome.</item>
            <item>Finally the <title>Guidelines</title> contain supporting appendices, such as the
                    <ref target="app-glossary.html">glossary of technical and specialized
                terms</ref>, and a <ref target="app-bibliography.html">bibliography</ref> of
                epigraphic and papyrological authorities, example EpiDoc corpora, and on digital
                publication of ancient texts generally. An <ref target="app-elements.html">index to
                    the <title>Guidelines</title> by TEI elements mentioned</ref> allows readers to
                find all epigraphic features in which a given element is part of the recommended
                usage.</item>
        </list>

        <p>Individual pages in the <title>Guidelines</title> are organised by epigraphic or
            papyrological concept, rather than by TEI element name. So, for instance, all pages
            involving abbreviations are grouped together (<ref
                target="app-alltrans.html#editorial-interventions">under the Editorial Interventions
                rubric</ref>), regardless of what TEI elements are specified. Each
                <title>Guidelines</title> page has a regular structure: first, a brief explanation of
            the title of a page (e.g., for <ref target="trans-uninterpreted.html">the page entitled
                ‘Uninterpreted Characters’</ref>, there is an explanation “Clear but incomprehensible
            letters”). The relevant TEI element (or elements) are displayed in a box underneath,
            including a link to the <title>TEI Guidelines</title> page for that element. There then
            follows a prose explanation of the EpiDoc recommendations for the use of those TEI
            elements, including details of relevant attributes and values.</p>

        <p>Below this explanation there are usually a few examples of the usage in context.
            Especially in the case of transcriptional features, the <title>Guidelines</title> will
            list conventional renderings of the issue in question according to common epigraphic or
            papyrological transcription guidelines, such as <term target="#krummreypanciera"
                >Krummrey-Panciera</term> and the <term target="#ddb">Duke Databank</term>.</p>

        <p>The XML examples show the recommended markup for the various types of each transcriptional
            feature, e. g. different cases of <ref target="trans-abbrevmark.html">expansion of an
                abbreviation which includes a symbol</ref>. The examples often list several markup options
            depending on the level of detail desired. Below the examples there is a series of
            renderings (or a different rendering after each example) which represent the several
            outputs available in the example EpiDoc P5 stylesheets. The default output is following
            the <term target="#krummreypanciera">Krummrey-Panciera</term> conventions. The others
            include the SEG style, the London style and the DDbDP style. Below each example there is
            a reference pointing to its source. Most of the examples are taken from the <term
                target="#iaph">Inscriptions of Aphrodisias</term>, the <term target="#irt"
                >Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</term> and the <term target="#ddb">Duke Databank
                of Documentary Papyri</term>. </p>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="more-de">
        <head>Training, Tools, and Support</head>
        
        <p>These <title>Guidelines</title> are in essence a reference source. For more in-depth
            training or support, other resources might be available. Members of the EpiDoc community
            run occasional training schools, sometimes funded by major projects (such as seve̛ral
            workshops run during the Inscriptions of Aphrodisias Project, 2004-2008); more
            information on these training events can be found on the <ref
                target="http://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/Training/">Training page in the EpiDoc
                Wiki</ref>. Those new to EpiDoc and text encoding might also find general training
            sessions on TEI (some listed in <ref
                target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Current_events">TEI Events list</ref>)
            useful.</p>

        <p>EpiDoc can be authored and edited using any standard tool for XML (several of which are
            listed on the <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Category:Editing_tools"
                >Editing Tools page of the TEI wiki</ref>); basic training in the use of such tools
            is usually included in both EpiDoc and TEI training events, or any XML tutorial. Other
            tools for publishing, searching and otherwise processing EpiDoc and TEI files include the
            XML transformation languages <ref target="http://www.w3schools.com/xsl/xsl_intro.asp"
                >XSLT</ref> and <ref target="http://www.w3schools.com/xquery/xquery_intro.asp"
                >XQuery</ref>, and general searching platforms such as <ref
                target="http://lucene.apache.org/solr/">Solr</ref> and TEI-specific open source tools
            like <ref target="https://github.com/kcl-ddh/kiln">Kiln</ref> and the <ref
                target="https://github.com/papyri/navigator">Papyrological Navigator</ref>.</p>

        <p>As always, the first port of call for help with any topic not covered by these guidelines
            should be the <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/MarkupList/">Markup
                list</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div xml:id="intro-intro-de-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Laura Löser</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Simona Stoyanova</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Charlotte Tupman</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Tom Elliott</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>translated to German</resp><name></name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
