<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008-2014 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-apparatus" xml:lang="en">
    <head xml:lang="la">Apparatus criticus</head>
    <p>Critical apparatus is a standard feature of scholarly editions in which variant readings and other
        philological comments are presented to readers as a compressed list immediately following the text, 
        organized by line numbers therein.</p>
    <!-- can have div's or p's  here. Divs are for subsections. -->
    <p><specList>
        <specDesc key="div"/>
    </specList></p>

    <p>Form and content of the apparatus varies from one discipline to another in the humanities.
        In manuscript studies and literary philology, the <abbr>app. crit.</abbr> is generally differentiated
        from a separate <ref target="supp-commentary.html">line-by-line commentary</ref>, 
        and is devoted narrowly to the documentation of variant readings found in extant witnesses.
        In epigraphic and papyrological practice, where there is normally only one ancient witness to a text,
        the apparatus regularly treats divergeant or erroneous readings published by prior editors,
        alternative restorations and emendations, and comments on form and appearance
        (e.g., transposition of letters) that cannot be clearly represented in the text itself. 
        Epigraphers and papyrologists often also include a commentary (line-by-line or otherwise) 
        in which more extended discussion of the text and its interpretation and historical significance can be addressed.</p>
    
    <p>EpiDoc recommends choosing between two methods of encoding
        the sort of information that is traditionally placed in the critical apparatus:</p>
    <p>Probably the most commonly used in EpiDoc projects is the 
        <ref target="supp-app-external.html">external approach</ref>
        (cf. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPLO">TEI "location-referenced"</ref>),
        in which the apparatus is encoded explicitly in a separate
        <tag>div type="apparatus"</tag> element. The individual apparatus entries in such an external division
        are tied back to the text using standard TEI linking attributes
        (generally <att>loc</att> pointing to line numbers).
        This method requires relatively simple XSLT to produce acceptable output, but the 
        <term target="'#epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc Example XSLT</term> does not currently cater for this out of the box.</p>
    <p>The <ref target="supp-app-inline.html">in-line approach</ref>
        (cf. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS">TEI "parallel segmentation method"</ref>)
        makes use of tags placed directly in the text,
        which can then be interpreted during post-processing for display in a line-by-line form.
        Currently the only EpiDoc project to have implemented this is the
        <ref target="#ddb">Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri</ref>,
        and any other project wishing to do so would need some significant work on the
        <term target="'#epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc Example XSLT</term>
        to get the behaviour it required.
    </p>
    
    <p>Specific guidance for each approach is provided in its own section as follows:</p>
    <list>
        <item><ref target="supp-app-external.html">External apparatus</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="supp-app-inline.html">In-line apparatus</ref></item>
    </list>
    <div xml:id="supp-apparatus-responsibility">
    
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Tom Elliott</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
