<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Copyright (C) 2000-2006 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-bibliography" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Encoding the Bibliography</head>
    <p>The bibliographical citations with an epigraphic/papyrological edition
        (to be distinguished from the master bibliography of a project or publication).</p>
    
    <div>
        <head>Master bibliography</head>
        <p>It is generally recommended that a master bibliography, containing all works cited
        in a publication or project (whether including discussions or only previous publications
        of texts) be encoded in a separate, single file. This might validate to the EpiDoc schema
        or to a generic TEI bibliographic schema, or could even be a free-standing database, or
        a HTML page with an <att>id</att> for each bibliographical entry.</p>
        
        <p>If encoding in TEI, the bibliography should comprise a structured list either of 
        <gi>bibl</gi> elements (recommended) or <gi>biblStruct</gi> elements (probably
        overkill for most projects, but see second example below). An <att>xml:id</att> on each
        item will allow referencing or linking from the localized bibliographic citations in
        individual texts.</p>
        
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="applebaum1979"><author>Shimon <surname>Applebaum</surname></author>,
                    <date>1979</date>, <title level="m">Jews and Greeks in Ancient Cyrene</title>,
                    <pubPlace>Leuven</pubPlace>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jmr1971a"><author>Joyce M. <surname>Reynolds</surname></author>,
                    <date>1971</date>, <title level="a">Zawiet Msus</title>,
                    <title level="j">Libya Antiqua</title> <biblScope type="issue">8</biblScope>,
                    <biblScope type="pp">39-42</biblScope></bibl>
            </listBibl>
        </egXML>
        
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <listBibl>
                <biblStruct xml:id="b0290">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><surname>Feissel</surname><forename>D.</forename></author>
                        <title level="a">Inscriptions byzantines de Ténos</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">BCH</title>
                        <imprint><date>1980</date></imprint>
                        <biblScope type="issue">104</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">477-518</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </listBibl>
        </egXML>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Bibliographic citations</head>
        <p>Individual texts will often contain multiple bibliographic citations, for example to works
        cited in commentary, the source of translations of photographs, and most importantly, to
        previous publications of the same text by other scholars. Within an EpiDoc edition, such
        citations should be contained in the <tag>div type="bibliography"</tag>, either in an
        unstructured <gi>p</gi> (if the bibliography is a paragraph of free text with connecting prose
        such as, "First published in ..., from notebooks; reprinted in ...; whence ... . Later re-edited from autopsy by..." etc.)
        or in a <gi>listBibl</gi> if the citations are a simple (or numbered) list.</p>
        
        <p>Each bibliographic citation may be encoded relatively simply in a <gi>bibl</gi> element
        in the form that is desired in the online (or print) edition, be that a full bibliographic reference or
        abbreviated author + date or similar. It is often useful, however, to link back to the entry in
        a bibliographic authority (generally the master bibliography), for example so that:
        <list type="ordered">
            <item>edition can hyperlink back from short title to a full or even annotated bibliography;</item>
            <item>bibliographic citations (full or short) can be automatically generated from the main
                bibliography, providing more consistency and reducing the need for multiple entry of
                identical information;</item>
            <item>a bibliographic concordance can be generated (using the <gi>idno</gi> of the current
            edition, the <att>xml:id</att> of the bibliographic item, and the <gi>citedRange</gi> of the 
            bibliographic citation in the edition.</item>
        </list>
        </p>
        
        <p>Assuming a master bibliography in TEI containing the entries from the first example above,
        the bibliographic citation below would (a) point to the Reynolds 1971 title therein, and (b) state
        unambiguously that the text in whose edition this citation appears was previously published as
        number 3 in her edition.</p>
        
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <bibl><ptr target="biblio.xml#jmr1971a"/> <citedRange>3</citedRange></bibl>
        </egXML>
        
        <p>This would allow, firstly, the edition to display text such as <q>Reynolds 1971, 3</q> or
        <q>Reynolds, 'Zawiet Msus' (1971), no. 3</q> or similar; and secondly a bibliographic
        concordance to be generated that lists all of the inscriptions in each previous publication,
        showing which inscription in the current collection corresponds to each. (See for example the
            <ref target="http://insaph.kcl.ac.uk/iaph2007/inscriptions/concordance/publication/jmr1980.html">InsAph
            concordance</ref> for a Reynolds article.)</p>

    </div>
    
    <div xml:id="supp-bibliography-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
