<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-translation" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Translation</head>
    <p>Tagging the translation of the text into English or another (usually modern) language.</p>
   
   <p>At the most general level, it is worth saying that almost anything that can be tagged in the
   transcribed text division of an epigraphic or papyrological edition can in principle also be tagged
   in the translation division. In practice, however, far less markup will appear in most translations,
   in some cases almost none at all.</p>
    
    <div>
        <head>Features of the division</head>
        <p>The translation or translations should be contained in a division of the body of the TEI file,
            with a <att>type</att> attribute identifying it as a translation division.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div type="translation"><p>...</p></div>
        </egXML>
        <p>The translation might be subcategorized in some way. For instance, an edition might contain
        more than one translation into a single language, according to a particular typology; the translation
        <gi>div</gi>s could therefore bear <att>subtype</att> attributes with values such as "literal", "poetic",
        "free" and so forth. Perhaps more commonly, an edition might encode translations in more than one
        modern language, which would then be differentiated by means of <att>xml:lang</att> attributes.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
                <p>In the year 6960, in the 13th (or 10th) indiction. With the Lord's help, the wall was completed. 
                    Christ, come as a Helper, to ... Kosta. In the year 6960.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="ru">
                <p>6960, в 13-й (или: 10-й) индикт (?). С [Божьей] помощью окончена стена. 
                    Приди Помощником, Христе, к ... Косте. В 6960 году.</p>
             </div>
        </egXML>
        <p>Separate translations might be encoded for different texts or parts of the text in an edition,
            perhaps most appropriately on a <tag>div type="textpart"</tag> within the translation division, rather
            than on the top-level division. Each translation might have an <ref target="supp-app-external.html">apparatus</ref> as well.
        The correspondence between parts of the transcription and of the translation might be recorded
        in an attribute such as <att>n</att> (giving the number or letter of the corresponding section), or
        more formally, <att>corresp</att>, linking directly to the <att>xml:id</att> of a division containing
        the corresponding text.</p>
        <p>Other means of differentiating multiple translations, using the various TEI attributes on <gi>div</gi>
        are imaginable.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Features of the translated text</head>
        <p>As noted above, the translation is likely to require far fewer features of markup than the 
        transcribed text itself. The features most commonly tagged in translations include:</p>
        <list>
            <item><ref target="trans-restored.html">Restored text</ref>: (<tag>supplied reason="lost"</tag>)
                to tag restored text (most often entire words or phrases,
            since the translation will seldom align with the original text more finely than this);</item>
            <item><ref target="trans-subaudible.html">Editor makes "subaudible" word
                manifest</ref>: (<tag>supplied reason="subaudible"</tag>)
                to tag words or phrases added by way of
            clarification in the translation that were not present in the transcription;</item>
            <item><ref target="trans-editorsnote.html">Editor's note</ref>: (<gi>note</gi>)
            to tag the editor's words that are not part of the translation per se, such as "i.e. 212 CE",
            or "unclear".</item>
            <item><ref target="trans-abbrevfully.html">Abbreviation fully expanded</ref>: (<gi>expan</gi>, <gi>ex</gi>)
            most often used to indicate names, if at all, abbreviated in the original;</item>
            <item><ref target="trans-lostcharunknown.html">Lost characters</ref> (<gi>gap</gi>)
            to indicate significant spans of lacuna in the original text.</item>
        </list>
    </div>
    
    <divGen type="seeAlso"/>
    
    <div xml:id="intro-faq-responsibility">
    <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
