<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Copyright (C) 2000-2006 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-historigdate" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Original date of text and/or object</head>
    <p>This section of the EpiDoc Guidelines provides direction for encoding the date of origin of the text (or in
        some cases, of the object or some other feature, decoration, or reuse of it), whether the result of the
        editor's analysis or an explicit, internal date. Guidance is also provided on recording possible ranges of
        dates, degrees of precision and dating criteria.</p>
    <div rend="tag-defs">
        <head>Relevant element documentation (TEI):</head>
        <p><specList>
                <specDesc key="origDate"/>
                <specDesc key="precision"/>
            </specList></p>
    </div>

    <div>

        


        <p> The date of orgin of the text (or object, if different) should be recorded in an <gi>origDate</gi> element
            in the <gi>origin</gi> section of the manuscript description area (see <ref target="supp-history.html">the
                general section on provenance</ref> for context). If different dates need to be recorded for text and
            object, different texts on the same support, or different interventions in the same text, the
                <gi>origDate</gi> may be repeated, or the entire <gi>history</gi> may be embedded in multiple
                <gi>msPart</gi>s. </p>

        <p> It is generally recommended to encode the dating information in numerical form, following the proleptic
            Julian calendar, using the att.datable.custom attributes on the <gi>origDate</gi> element. These "custom"
            date attributes are required because the default dating system assumed by the basic TEI date attributes
            (att.datable) is the Gregorian calendar. Moreover, therefore, the dating element should always carry a
                <att>datingMethod</att> attribute pointing to a <gi>calendar</gi> element in the header--or to an
            external authority for the Julian calendar, such as http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_calendar.</p>

        <p> A specific date, whether a single day, month, or year in the Julian calendar, can be expressed using the
                <att>when-custom</att> attribute, which should be laid out in the same form as an <ref
                target="http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime">ISO 8601/W3C date</ref> (albeit in the Julian, not Gregorian
            calendar). In other words: <list type="ordered">
                <item>A year should be encoded in four digits, with leading zeroes as necessary (i.e. 14 C.E. should be
                    "0014")</item>
                <item>B.C.E./B.C. dates should be recorded as negative numbers (i.e. preceded by "-"); NB there is no
                    year "0"</item>
                <item>Month and day should be encoded in two digits, with leading zero as necessary (i.e. January 7th
                    should be "--01-07")</item>
                <item>A year may appear without months or day; a year+month may appear without day</item>
            </list>
        </p>

        <p> A date within a range (such as the reign of an emperor, or a century for e.g. palaeographically dated text)
            should be encoded using the <att>notBefore-custom</att> and <att>notAfter-custom</att> attributes, marking
            the beginning and end of the possible span of dates. The date formats of these attributes are the same as
            for <gi>when-custom</gi>. </p>

        <p>This example encodes a simple Julian date:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origDate when-custom="0139" datingMethod="#julian">139 C.E.</origDate>
        </egXML>
        <p>This example encodes a date range, again in Julian calendar:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origDate 
             notBefore-custom="-0020-12-11" 
             notAfter-custom="-0019-12-10" 
             datingMethod="#julian">December 11th, 20 to December 10th, 19 B.C.E.</origDate>
        </egXML>
        <p>This example uses the custom dating attributes on the <gi>origDate</gi> element to express a date in the
            Julian calendar that is derived from a date recorded on an inscription in the <ref
                target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shalivahana_era">Śaka era</ref>.</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><origDate 
notBefore-custom="1409" 
notAfter-custom="1410"
datingMethod="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_calendar">The text records a composition 
  date of <date 
   calendar="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shalivahana_era">1331</date>(Śaka)</origDate>
</egXML>

        <div>
            <head>Certainty and precision</head>
            <p> Not all texts are dated confidently to a specific year or firm span of years. If a date given is flagged
                explicitly as less certain than usual (for example, either with a "?" or a formulation such as "just
                possibly") the <gi>origDate</gi> may be given a <att>cert</att> attribute with a value of "low". If a
                date is flagged as approximate (which is different from being uncertain; often written "circa", "ca." or
                "c.") <gi>origDate</gi> should be given an <att>precision</att> with a value of low. If a date range is
                specified (with <att>notBefore-custom</att> and <att>notAfter-custom</att>) whose start and end points
                are essentially arbitrary, such as a century or half-century for a palaeographical date, then a
                    <att>precision</att> of "medium" should be given, to indicate that the start and end-points are both
                notional. </p>
            <p> In a few cases, a text may be dated within a span of dates with a notional end-point but a firm <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">terminus post quem</foreign>. To record this in XML, a <gi>precision</gi> element may
                be placed inside the <gi>origDate</gi> to point to whichever of the attributes represents the less
                concrete end-point. (See third example below.) </p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate notBefore-custom="-0100" notAfter-custom="0100" precision="medium" datingMethod="#julian">
                    First century B.C. to first century A.D. </origDate>
            </egXML>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate when-custom="-0355" precision="low" datingMethod="#julian"> Circa 355 B.C.E. </origDate>
            </egXML>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><origDate 
notBefore-custom="0015"  
notAfter-custom="0050" 
datingMethod="#julian">First half first century C.E., but certainly after the death of Augustus. 
  <precision match="../@notBefore-custom" precision="high"/>
  <precision match="../@notAfter-custom" precision="medium"/>
</origDate>
</egXML>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head>Dating criteria</head>
            <p>... @evidence, suggest typology, example values ...</p>
            <p>Cf <ref target="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0As1AGmWRrRdUdGNJWm9HdDhsQ0RkRFc4dkQwZGZQRVE"
                    >EpiDoc dating criteria vocabulary</ref> (Google Spreadsheet)</p>


            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate 
                 notBefore-custom="0367" 
                 notAfter-custom="0400" 
                 precision="medium"
                 evidence="lettering nomenclature" 
                 datingMethod="#julian"> Late fourth century (lettering and nomenclature). </origDate>
            </egXML>
        </div>

    </div>
    <div xml:id="intro-faq-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt>
                    <resp>author</resp>
                    <name>Gabriel Bodard</name>
                </respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
