<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Header: https://epidoc.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/epidoc/trunk/guidelines/xml-p5/xml/introeps.xml 1159 2010-05-14 11:02:59Z paregorios $ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-historigin" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Original location of the text-bearing object</head>

    <p>As discussed in <ref target="supp-history.html">the general section on provenance</ref>, information about the
        origin and subsequent history of a text-bearing object is collected in a <gi>history</gi> element that is part
        of the <gi>msDesc</gi> in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. An <gi>origin</gi> element is used within <gi>history</gi>,
        and its child element <gi>origPlace</gi> is used for topographic and geographic assertions associated with the
        object's origin. <gi>origPlace</gi> is normally accompanied by an <gi>origDate</gi> element (<ref
            target="supp-historigdate.html">q.v.</ref>), which is used to encode information about the date of
        origin.</p>
    <div rend="tag-defs">
        <head>Relevant element documentation (TEI):</head>
        <p>
            <specList>
                <specDesc key="history"/>
                <specDesc key="msDesc"/>
                <specDesc key="origin"/>
                <specDesc key="origDate"/>
                <specDesc key="origPlace"/>
                <specDesc key="p"/>
                <specDesc key="placeName"/>
                <specDesc key="provenance"/>
                <specDesc key="rs"/>
                <specDesc key="seg"/>
                <specDesc key="teiHeader"/>
            </specList>
        </p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <p><gi>origPlace</gi> has the same basic content model in the TEI as a <gi>p</gi> (paragraph) tag, so its contents
        can range from plain text to highly structured and cross-linked data (or a combination of both).</p>
        <p><gi>origPlace</gi> can carry both the <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes. EpiDoc does not require the use of these attributes, nor does it constrain their values via the schema; however, the following values for the <att>type</att> attribute are recommended if useful for a given project:</p>
        <table>
            <row role="label">
                <cell><att>type</att></cell>
                <cell>notes</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>composed</cell>
                <cell>place of original (ancient) composition of the text</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>executed</cell>
                <cell>place of original (ancient) execution of the text; i.e., where the physical support was when the text we have was placed upon it</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>sent</cell>
                <cell>for a letter or other transmitted document: whence it was dispatched in antiquity</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>received</cell>
                <cell>for a letter or other transmitted document: where it was delivered in antiquity</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>stored</cell>
                <cell>for a portable document, such as a codex or papyrus roll, where it was habitually stored in antiquity</cell>
            </row>
        </table>
        <p>The following
        examples illustrate some of the options.</p>

    <div>
        <head>Plain-text examples</head>

        <p>A simple, plain-text example that assumes a narrow topographic context implied by the framing publication or
            corpus:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>Probably from the cella wall.</origPlace>
        </egXML>
        <p>A more expanded example providing geographic context might be written thus:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>Probably from the cella wall of the temple of Aphrodite at Aphrodisias.</origPlace>
        </egXML>

        <p>A plain-text assertion that the place of origin is coincident with the <ref target="supp-histfound.html"
                >place of finding</ref> (which is presumably described appropriately in a <gi>provenance</gi> element
            elsewhere in the <gi>history</gi>):</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>Findspot.</origPlace>
        </egXML>

        <p>TEI markup can be added to deal with a wide variety of details, as in this example where multiple languages
            and writing systems are used:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace ref="origPlace.xml#p003" n="1">
                <seg xml:lang="ru">Херсон</seg>
                <seg xml:lang="en">Chersonesos</seg>
            </origPlace>
        </egXML>

    </div>

    <div>
        <head>Structured data and links to gazetteers and other controlled vocabularies</head>

        <p>Best practice is to mark placenames as such, using the appropriate TEI <gi>placeName</gi> element:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>All commentators agree that the altar must originally have been placed somewhere on the
                site of ancient <placeName type="ancient">Veii</placeName>.</origPlace>
        </egXML>

        <p>The information in the <gi>origPlace</gi> could be linked to an internal list of places/monuments with a
                <att>key</att></p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>Perhaps <rs type="monuList" key="db1047">Shrine of the 
                Dioscuri</rs></origPlace>
        </egXML>

        <p>The <att>ref</att> attribute can be used to link to a project-specific or external list or gazetteer that
            makes use of HTTP Uniform Resource Identifiers (URIs) to identify individual structures or places:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <origPlace>Perhaps from the <rs type="monuList" key="db1047">Shrine of the Dioscuri</rs> 
                at <placeName ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/423025">Rome</placeName>.</origPlace>
        </egXML>
    </div>

    <div>
        <head>Linking place of origin to place of finding</head>
        <p>In one of the simple examples above, the word "Findspot" was put inside <gi>origPlace</gi> to assert that the
            text-bearing object was found <foreign xml:lang="la">in situ</foreign>. Some projects may want to be able to
            use software to identify programmatically and exploit such situations for fuller output, map-making, index
            creation, and the like. It is possible to write a script or transform that, upon encountering such a
            construct, attempts to look up a <gi>provenance</gi> element with the standard <att>type</att>="found"
            attribute value in the same file; however, it is not difficult to make such a cross reference more readily
            machine actionable in the XML. By using the <att>corresp</att> attribute to link <gi>origPlace</gi> to a
                <gi>provenance</gi> element that carries an <att>xml:id</att> attribute with a matching value, such
            connections are rendered more consistent and reliable. Note that any corresponding ID value could be used;
            "findspot" was chosen for this example because it is readily meaningful to the human reader.</p>

        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <history>
                <origin>
                    <origPlace corresp="#findspot">Findspot.</origPlace>
                </origin>
                <provenance xml:id="findspot" type="found">Found in the Carrer de Llibreteria, 
                    Barcelona</provenance>
            </history>
        </egXML>

        <p>The same technique is used in this extended example:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
<history>
 
 <origin>
  <origPlace corresp="#findspot">
   The shrine of  <placeName type="modern" key="cic-geo:drang-lai">Drang Lai</placeName> 
   in the town (<foreign>thị xã</foreign>) of Ayun Pa (formerly Cheo Reo), in the modern 
   province of Gia Lai.
  </origPlace>
 </origin>
 
 <provenance xml:id="findspot" type="found" notAfter="1901">
  <ab>The inscription was first mentioned as being at 
   <placeName type="modern" key="cic-geo:drang-lai">Cheo Reo</placeName> in a report, 
   based on observations of <quote>an annamite</quote>, from missionary J.-B. Guerlach 
   cited in BEFEO 1 (1901), p. 413.</ab>
 </provenance>
 
 <provenance type="observed" when="1902">
  <ab>It was observed again by a certain Stenger (see BEFEO and 2 (1902), p. 227); 
   presence at “Cheo Reo” described by <bibl><ptr target="cic-bibl:parmentier-1902"/>: 
   282</bibl>; proper provenance ascertained by Prosper Odend’hal in 1903 (see 
   <bibl><ptr target="cic-bibl:finot-1904b"/>: 535</bibl>). The stela was described in 
   <bibl><ptr target="cic-bibl:parmentier-1909"/>: 562-563</bibl>.<note>Two published 
   photographs show the stela when it was placed at the temple of Yang Mum: fig. 129 on 
   <bibl><ptr target="cic-bibl:parmentier-1909"/>: 561</bibl> and photo 181 in 
   <bibl><ptr target="cic-bibl:ghesquiere-2005"/></bibl>.</note></ab>
 </provenance>
 
 <provenance type="observed" when="1927">
  <ab>It was received at the EFEO Museum in Tourane in 1927, as reported in BEFEO 27, 
   p. 460.<note><quote>Le Musée a reçu par les soins du Résident de Kontum les sculptures 
   et inscriptions provenant de Draṅ-lai et de Yaṅ Mum qui avaient été groupées à la 
   Résidence. C’est ainsi que la grande statue de Çiva qui trônait sur l’autel du temple 
   de Yaṅ Mum (<hi rend="italic">IC.</hi>, I, p. 561), le Çiva sur Nandin, le petit Çiva 
   assis devant un chevet inscrit au dos, et la stèle inscrite sur trois faces 
   (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 562, Liste Cœdès, C. 42-43), ces trois dernières 
   pièces provenant de Draṅ-lai, ont trouvé au Musée un asile plus sûr que celui qu’il 
   avait été possible de leur assurer jusqu’ici.</quote></note></ab>
 </provenance>
 
 <provenance type="observed" when="1986">
  <ab>The stela was removed from the Museum under unknown circumstances at an unknown 
   point of time, no doubt during the turbulent period between WW II and Vietnamese 
   reunification in 1975. It resurfaced when it was acquired by the Museum of Fine Art 
   in Boston (USA) in 1986, where it was recorded under <ptr target="#inv-MFA"/>.</ab>
 </provenance>
 
</history>
</egXML>

    </div>
    </div>
    
    <divGen type="seealso"/>

    <div xml:id="supp-historigin-responsibility">

        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Simona Stoyanova</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Tom Elliott</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Arlo Griffiths</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>James Cowey</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Scott Vanderbilt</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
