<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-apparatus" xml:lang="en">
    <head xml:lang="la">Apparatus criticus</head>
    <p>Critical apparatus is a standard feature of scholarly editions in which variant readings and other
        philological comments are presented to readers as a compressed list immediately following the text, 
        organized by line numbers therein.</p>
    <!-- can have div's or p's  here. Divs are for subsections. -->
    <p><specList>
        <specDesc key="div"/>
    </specList></p>

    <p>Form and content of the apparatus varies from one discipline to another in the humanities.
        In manuscript studies and literary philology, the <abbr>app. crit.</abbr> is generally differentiated
        from a separate <ref target="supp-commentary.html">line-by-line commentary</ref>, 
        and is devoted narrowly to the documentation of variant readings found in extant witnesses.
        In epigraphic and papyrological practice, where there is normally only one ancient witness to a text,
        the apparatus regularly treats divergeant or erroneous readings published by prior editors,
        alternative restorations and emendations, and comments on form and appearance
        (e.g., transposition of letters) that cannot be clearly represented in the text itself. 
        Epigraphers and papyrologists often also include a commentary (line-by-line or otherwise) 
        in which more extended discussion of the text and its interpretation and historical significance can be addressed.</p>
    
    <p>EpiDoc recommends choosing between two methods of encoding
        the sort of information that is traditionally placed in the critical apparatus:</p>
    <p>Probably the most commonly used in EpiDoc projects is the 
        <ref target="supp-app-external.html">external approach</ref>
        (cf. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPLO">TEI "location-referenced"</ref>),
        in which the apparatus is encoded explicitly in a separate
        <tag>div type="apparatus"</tag> element. The individual apparatus entries in such an external division
        are tied back to the text using standard TEI linking attributes
        (generally <att>loc</att> pointing to line numbers).
        This method requires relatively simple XSLT to produce acceptable output, but the 
        <term target="'#epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc Example XSLT</term> does not currently cater for this out of the box.</p>
    
    <p>The <ref target="supp-app-inline.html">in-line approach</ref>
        (cf. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS">TEI "parallel segmentation method"</ref>)
        makes use of tags placed directly in the text,
        which can then be interpreted during post-processing for display in a line-by-line form.
        Currently the only EpiDoc project to have implemented this is the
        <ref target="#ddb">Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri</ref>,
        and any other project wishing to do so would need some significant work on the
        <term target="'#epidoc-stylesheets">EpiDoc Example XSLT</term>
        to get the behaviour it required.
    </p>
    
    <p>There are a number of features which you may want to appear in your apparatus or in a separate apparatus section, which are not explicitly encoded as apparatus notes with either of the
    above methods. <ref target="supp-app-stylesheets.html">The EpiDoc example Stylesheets</ref> provide some support to render these in several ways.</p>
    <p>It is very important to decide on the approach you want to follow and remain consistent to that, to avoid inconsistencies, although both methods are acceptable 
        and independent of the way you may
        want to display or not your apparatus notes. The fact that you decide to use <gi>app</gi> in the text, following the in-line approach, does not dictate automatically that you want an apparatus 
    which includes also other features, as the fact  that you use the external approach does not dictate that you do not want anything which you have actually encoded in the text to be printed in an apparatus section. These
    things are determined at the level of the rendering, not with the encoding, and you may chose what to do, as far as you are consistent with yourself.</p>
    <p>Although the external-apparatus approach is the recommended way to encode apparatus notes, you may wish not to have to produce one such note in <tag>div[@type='apparatus']</tag> for each
        <gi>choice</gi> element you encoded and want in an apparatus. To inform your encoding decision, here you can find a list of the possibilities currently 
        offered by the <ref target="supp-app-stylesheets.html">The EpiDoc example Stylesheets</ref>.</p>
    
    <p>Specific guidance for each approach is provided in its own section as follows:</p>
    <list>
        <item><ref target="supp-app-external.html">External apparatus</ref></item>
        <item><ref target="supp-app-inline.html">In-line apparatus</ref></item>
    </list>
    
    <divGen type="seealso"/>
    
    <div xml:id="supp-apparatus-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Tom Elliott</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
