<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xml:id="supp-structure" 
    xml:lang="en">
    <head>Structure of an EpiDoc edition</head>
    <p>This section introduces the structure and shape of an EpiDoc edition, 
        introducing the TEI P5 approach to manuscript description and history,
        the divisions in the body, etc.</p>
    
    <p>
        <specList>
            <specDesc key="msDesc"/>
        </specList>
    </p>
    
    <p>Most of the features that most commonly occur in an epigraphic/papyrological edition are catered for
        by specific locations in an EpiDoc file. This document aims to give an overview of those locations.
        Individual pages in the <ref target="app-allsupp.html">Supporting Data</ref> section of the Guidelines
        will give more detailed information on each of these elements and features.</p>
    
    <p>A relatively simple EpiDoc file containing descriptive and historical information about an inscription might look
        something like the following example. A version of this example, keyed to the latest version of the EpiDoc
        schema and suitable for use as a project template, may be downloaded from the EpiDoc website: <ref
            target="ex-epidoctemplate.xml?format=raw">ex-epidoctemplate.xml</ref>.</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <xi:include href="ex-epidoctemplate.xml"/>
    </egXML>
    
    <div>
        <head>Edition</head>
        <p><gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> of "edition".
            The edition division contains the epigraphic, papyrological (etc.) text itself as well as editorial interventions
            (i.e. representations in EpiDoc of the Leiden sigla) that are to be applied to the text.
            Leiden equivalence is a minimum requirement; further detail on editorial interventions can be included as required.
            <att>xml:lang</att> is a required attribute, unless textparts have individual languages (see immediately below).</p>
        <p>The edition division can be divided using <gi>div</gi> elements with an <att>type</att> of "textpart", which is a constrained value.
            If textparts have individual languages, <att>xml:lang</att> should be added to each textpart.
            An edition may have any number of textparts, which can be further subdivided using <att>subtype</att> with unconstrained values
            (e.g. "fragment", "column" or whatever description is relevant to that particular text).
            For detailed discussion and examples see <ref target="app-alltrans.html">List Of All Transcription Guidelines</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Translation</head>
        <p><gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> of "translation".
            The translation division follows the same rules as for the edition, but will usually contains much less markup, and is likely to have a simpler structure.
        The language of the translation division can be encoded using <att>lang</att> (with two- or three- letter language codes e.g. "de", "fr", "en").
        The source or responsibility for the translation can be encoded using <att>source</att> or <att>resp</att>.
        The translation division can be given a <att>subtype</att> (unconstrained) to describe it further, e.g. "literal", "literary", "pedagogical" etc.
            For detailed discussion and examples see <ref target="supp-translation.html">Translation</ref></p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Apparatus</head>
        <p><gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> of "apparatus".
        The TEI apparatus module is designed for Lachmannian <hi rend="italic">apparatus criticus</hi>, which allows for multiple witnesses to a text.
        The epigraphic <hi rend="italic">apparatus criticus</hi> is likely to include comments on letterforms; supplements; interpretations; and the readings of previous editors.
            For detailed discussion and examples see <ref target="supp-apparatus.html">Apparatus Criticus</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Commentary</head>
        <p><gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> of "commentary".
        The commentary division will usually be written in prose, and might contain general discussion of the context of the text or the support, further information about dating criteria, external references, comments on specific sections of the text etc.</p>
    </div>
    
    <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <p><gi>div</gi> with <att>type</att> of "bibliography".
        The bibliography division can contain both free-standing content and links to the master bibliography, using <gi>listBibl</gi> with any number of <gi>bibl</gi> elements.
        This division can be subdivided further using <att>subtype</att> with unconstrained values that might include e.g. "principal", "derived", "discussion" etc.
            For detailed discussion and examples see <ref target="supp-bibliography.html">Encoding the Bibliography</ref>.</p>
    </div>
    
    <divGen type="seealso"/>
    
    <div xml:id="supp-structure-responsibility">    
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>Author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>Author</resp><name>Charlotte Tupman</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
