<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="supp-historigdate" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Original date of text and/or object</head>
    <p>This section of the EpiDoc Guidelines provides direction for encoding the date of origin of
        the text (or in some cases, of the object or some other feature, decoration, or reuse of
        it), whether the result of the editor's analysis or an explicit, internal date. Guidance is
        also provided on recording possible ranges of dates, named historical periods,
        degrees of precision and dating criteria.</p>
    <div rend="tag-defs">
        <head>Relevant element documentation (TEI):</head>
        <p>
            <specList>
                <specDesc key="origDate"/>
                <specDesc key="precision"/>
            </specList>
        </p>
    </div>

    <div>
            <p> The date of orgin of the text (or object, if different) should be recorded in an
                    <gi>origDate</gi> element in the <gi>origin</gi> section of the manuscript
                description area (see <ref target="supp-history.html">the general section on
                    provenance</ref> for context). If different dates need to be recorded for text and
                object, different texts on the same support, or different interventions in the same
                text, the <gi>origDate</gi> may be repeated, or the entire <gi>history</gi> may be
                embedded in multiple <gi>msPart</gi>s. </p>
    
            <p> It is generally recommended to encode the dating information in numerical form,
                following the proleptic Julian calendar, using the att.datable.custom attributes on the
                    <gi>origDate</gi> element. These "custom" date attributes are required because the
                default dating system assumed by the basic TEI date attributes (att.datable) is the
                Gregorian calendar. Moreover, therefore, the dating element should always carry a
                    <att>datingMethod</att> attribute pointing to a <gi>calendar</gi> element in the
                header--or to an external authority for the Julian calendar, such as
                http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_calendar.</p>
    
            <p> A specific date, whether a single day, month, or year in the Julian calendar, can be
                expressed using the <att>when-custom</att> attribute, which should be laid out in the
                same form as an <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime">ISO 8601/W3C date</ref>
                (albeit in the Julian, not Gregorian calendar). In other words: <list type="ordered">
                    <item>A year should be encoded in four digits, with leading zeroes as necessary
                        (i.e. 14 C.E. should be "0014")</item>
                    <item>B.C.E./B.C. dates should be recorded as negative numbers (i.e. preceded by
                        "-"); NB there is no year "0"</item>
                    <item>Month and day should be encoded in two digits, with leading zero as necessary
                        (i.e. January 7th should be "--01-07")</item>
                    <item>A year may appear without months or day; a year+month may appear without
                        day</item>
                </list>
            </p>
    
        <div>
            <head>Date range</head>
            <p> A date within a range (such as an event occurring within the reign of an emperor, e.g.,
                the raising of a milestone, or a century for, e.g., palaeographically dated text) should
                be encoded using the <att>notBefore-custom</att> and <att>notAfter-custom</att>
                attributes, marking the beginning and end of the possible span of dates. The date
                formats of these attributes are the same as for <att>when-custom</att>.</p>
    
            <p>This example encodes a simple Julian date:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate when-custom="0139" datingMethod="#julian">139 C.E.</origDate>
            </egXML>
            <p>This example encodes a date occurring within a range, again in Julian calendar:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate notBefore-custom="-0020-12-11" notAfter-custom="-0019-12-10"
                    datingMethod="#julian">December 11th, 20 to December 10th, 19 B.C.E.</origDate>
            </egXML>
            <p>This example uses the custom dating attributes on the <gi>origDate</gi> element to
                express a date in the Julian calendar that is derived from a date recorded on an
                inscription in the <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shalivahana_era">Śaka
                    era</ref>. (The <att>calendar</att> attribute records the calendrical system of the
                date recorded by this element, wheras <att>datingMethod</att> records the system to
                which the date is normalized in the <att>xx-custom</att> attributes. Normalization would
                otherwise be assumed to be to the Gregorian calendar.)</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><origDate notBefore-custom="1409" notAfter-custom="1410" datingMethod="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_calendar">The text records a composition 
                   date of <date calendar="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shalivahana_era">1331</date>(Śaka)</origDate>
            </egXML>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head>Certainty and precision</head>
            <p> Not all texts are dated confidently to a specific year or firm span of years. If a
                date given is flagged explicitly as less certain than usual (for example, either
                with a "?" or a formulation such as "just possibly") the <gi>origDate</gi> may be
                given a <att>cert</att> attribute with a value of "low". If a date is flagged as
                approximate (which is different from being uncertain; often written "circa", "ca."
                or "c.") <gi>origDate</gi> should be given an <att>precision</att> with a value of
                low. If a date range is specified (with <att>notBefore-custom</att> and
                    <att>notAfter-custom</att>) whose start and end points are essentially
                arbitrary, such as a century or half-century for a palaeographical date, then a
                    <att>precision</att> of "medium" should be given, to indicate that the start and
                end-points are both notional. </p>
            <p> In a few cases, a text may be dated within a span of dates with a notional end-point
                but a firm <foreign xml:lang="la">terminus post quem</foreign>. To record this in
                XML, a <gi>precision</gi> element may be placed inside the <gi>origDate</gi> to
                point to whichever of the attributes represents the less concrete end-point. (See
                third example below.) </p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate notBefore-custom="-0100" notAfter-custom="0100" precision="medium"
                    datingMethod="#julian"> First century B.C. to first century A.D. </origDate>
            </egXML>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate when-custom="-0355" precision="low" datingMethod="#julian"> Circa 355
                    B.C.E. </origDate>
            </egXML>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><origDate notBefore-custom="0015" notAfter-custom="0050" datingMethod="#julian">First half first century C.E., but certainly after the death of Augustus. 
  <precision match="../@notBefore-custom" precision="high"/>
  <precision match="../@notAfter-custom" precision="medium"/>
</origDate>
</egXML>
            
            <p>You can align your definitions by aligning to a local or to an external
                <ref target="idx-nontei.html">Controlled Vocabulary</ref>.</p>
            
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <head>Named historical periods</head>
            <p>In some cases, rather than (or as well as) a specific or approximate numerical date range,
            scholars will date an inscription by a named historical period, such as "Hellenistic," "Imperial,"
            "Byzantine" or "Early Dynastic." If desired, the historical period may be encoded in the 
            <gi>origDate</gi> element using the <att>period</att> attribute, pointing to the <term>URI</term>
            of a vocabulary for historical periods such as <ref target="http://perio.do/">PeriodO</ref>
                or a <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q11514315#inverseclaims">Wikidata entity</ref>. (This period need not correspond precisely to the numerical date range
            offered, if any.)</p>
            
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate notBefore="-0332" notAfter="-0200" precision="medium"
                    period="http://n2t.net/ark:/99152/p0m63njc4hd" evidence="lettering">
                    Early Hellenistic (lettering)</origDate>
            </egXML>
        
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate when="-3000" precision="low"
                    period="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q187979" evidence="context">
                    Early Dynastic Period (context)</origDate>
            </egXML>
        </div>

        <div>
            <head>Dating criteria</head>
            <p>The criteria for the date given in the <gi>origDate</gi> element may be expressed in
                the <att>evidence</att> attribute. The contents of this attribute should be thought
                of as a series of space-delimited tokens rather than a sentence of prose. That is to
                say, for example, if the dating of an inscription depends on lettering, nomenclature
                and partly archaeological context, rather than encoding this as <tag rend="no"
                    >origDate evidence="lettering, nomenclature and partly archaeological
                    context"</tag> it would be more appropriate to enter: <tag>origDate
                    evidence="lettering nomenclature archaeological_context"</tag>. Note that
                because values in this list are space-delimited, any values that are multi-word
                phrases should have some symbol, generally hyphen ('-') in place of spaces. Most
                projects will find it useful to have a typology of criteria with a controlled
                vocabulary of values for the terms in this attribute.</p>
            <p>The EpiDoc schema suggests a short list of values for <att>evidence</att> to
                encourage consistency. These values are:</p>
            <list type="gloss">
                <item>
                    <term>archaeological-context</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by the archaeological context, stratigraphy or associated finds</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>internal-date</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by explicit internal date</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>lettering</term>
                    <gloss>Dated palaeographically</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>material-context</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by the material, technique or other physical context of the object itself</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>nomenclature</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by nomenclature or onomastics</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>office</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by an office or rank, e.g. the reign of an emperor or other ruler
                    </gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>prosopography</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by known persons named or implied within the text</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>textual-content</term>
                    <gloss>Dated via textual or linguistic context (other than explicit date, names or titles)
                    </gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>titulature</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by the use of official titles</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>iconography</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by the subject or theme depicted in the art associated with the inscription</gloss>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <term>artistic-style</term>
                    <gloss>Dated by stylistic or decorative features of the art associated with the inscription</gloss>
                </item>
            </list>
            <p>As these are only suggestions, there is no prohibition against any project using,
                e.g., “palaeography” instead of lettering or “onomastics” instead of nomenclature, or indeed use several terms that are more specific subcategories of “material context”. In any case it would be more advisable to maintain an internal table of dating criteria
                values, with the terms mapped to human-readable language (which might, for
                example, not be in English). Most projects will define their own lists, or use external LOD vocabularies such as <ref target="https://www.eagle-network.eu/resources/vocabularies/">EAGLE</ref>, <ref target="https://ontology.inscriptiones.org/">FAIR Epigraphy</ref>, <ref target="https://thesaurus.mom.fr/?idt=th61">Biblissima EpiVoc</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Wikidata:WikiProject_Epigraphy">Wikidata</ref>.</p>
            <p>Cf. <list><item><ref
                    target="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0As1AGmWRrRdUdGNJWm9HdDhsQ0RkRFc4dkQwZGZQRVE"
                    >EpiDoc dating criteria vocabularies</ref> (Google Spreadsheet)</item>
                <item><ref target="http://www.eagle-network.eu/voc/dates.html">EAGLE vocabulary - Dating Criteria</ref> (SKOS)</item>
            </list></p>
            
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate notBefore-custom="0367" notAfter-custom="0400" precision="medium"
                    evidence="lettering nomenclature" datingMethod="#julian">Late fourth century
                    (lettering and nomenclature).</origDate>
            </egXML>

            <p>This example encodes a certain date within a particular consular year:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <origDate when-custom="0152-08-23" precision="high" evidence="consulship"
                    datingMethod="#julian">23 August 152 C.E.</origDate>
                <!-- ... Glabrione et H[om]ulo co(n)s(ulibus) (a(nte) d(iem)) X K(alendas) Sept(embres)
                          (RIB 309) -->
            </egXML>

        </div>
    </div>
    
    <divGen type="seealso"/>
    
    <div xml:id="intro-faq-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
           <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Nora White</name></respStmt></bibl>
           <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Scott Vanderbilt</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
