<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 
    
    EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
    Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
    Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.
    
    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
    of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
    
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.
    
    Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
    http://epidoc.sf.net.
    
    End license statement: do not remove -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>
<div xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="trans-whitespace">
    <head>Managing Whitespace in Transcriptions</head>

    <p><specList>
        <specDesc key="expan"/>
    </specList>
        <!--<listRef>
            <ptr target="a"/>
            </listRef>--></p>
    
    <p>In diplomatic and edited transcriptions, default Epidoc whitespace handling may not always
        produce expected results. Problems arise in several situations, the most common of which is
        spaces that appear before or after a phrase-level element. XML treats whitespace differently
        when it occurs inside an element that is defined to contain only subelements and no free
        text, and elements whose definition allows a mixture of text and other elements. In the
        first case, whitespace around the contained elements will be ignored. In the second case,
        spaces and returns will be treated as actual text, and will appear in formatted output as a
        single space. This is complicated by the way that editors such as oXygen XML handle wrapping
        of lines - lines that are wrapped for readability do not have space or linefeed characters
        separating them, they just appear to.</p>

    <p>In the examples below, <gi>expan</gi> takes subelements <gi>abbr</gi> and <gi>ex</gi>
        as well as free text. In the second case, spaces before or after the subelements
        result in spaces appearing in the output. </p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" rend="panciera">
        <expan><abbr>Aug</abbr><ex>ustus</ex></expan>
    </egXML>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve" rend="panciera">
        <expan>
            <abbr>Aug</abbr>
            <ex>ustus</ex>
        </expan>
    </egXML>
    
    <p>The following example will have no spaces around any of the parts of the abbreviation. However, if there were any line feeds inside <gi>expan</gi>
    they would be preserved.</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"  rend="ddbdp"
        corresp="http://papyri.info/ddbdp/bgu;1;154">
        <expan>Καρ<ex>ανίδι</ex></expan>
    </egXML>

    <p>If spaces appear in formatted Epidoc output where they don't belong, the first thing to do is
        to check the XML source files for spaces or linefeeds have been inserted during the encoding
        process, often for readability.</p>

    <p>In some cases, for example when encoding inscriptions in Hebrew or Arabic that use a
        right-to-left writing system, it is necessary to use line feeds before tags, in order to
        preserve directionality. When preserving whitespace exactly as it is entered is important,
        you must set the <tag>xsl:preserve-space</tag> property at the beginning of your xsl
        transformation file and identify the elements to which this applies. Then, you can manage
        the whitespace explicitly during the formatting process.</p>

    <divGen type="seealso"/>

    <div xml:id="trans-whitespace-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Elli Mylonas</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
