<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 

EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.

This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
http://epidoc.sf.net.

End license statement: do not remove -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="trans-textpart" xml:lang="en">
    <head>Textpart</head>
    <p>Divisions of the edited text such as fragments, columns, chapters or versions in different languages.</p>
    <p>
        <specList>
            <specDesc key="ab"/>
            <specDesc key="div"/>
            <specDesc key="milestone"/>
        </specList>
    </p>

    <p>Units of the text that are separated and usually numbered independently by
        epigraphers and papyrologists—including fragments, columns, sections, chapters, independent texts on a single
        stone, marks, stamps, or graffiti grouped together—should be divided and
        numbered on the same basis in EpiDoc. The use of XML should not change the need for
        dividing and numbering the text in a way that makes semantic and intuitive sense to the editor.</p>
        
    <p>When a physical break in the support coincides with a major semantic break in the text,
        each text section should be wrapped in a separate <gi>ab</gi> inside a <gi>div</gi> with a <att>type</att>="textpart".
        This can be the case of non-contiguous fragments, inscriptions consisting of physically distinct parts with the same text in more 
        languages, or columns with loosely related content.</p>
    <p>It is highly recommended to provide an <att>n</att> attribute specifying an identifier for each <tag>div type="textpart"</tag>.
        It is often useful (although not obligatory) also to provide a <att>subtype</att> attribute naming the kind of subdivision
        of text being recorded; <att>subtype</att> is not constrained, but common values might include
        "fragment", "column", "face", "section", etc.
    </p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="a">
            <ab>
                <lb n="1"/>...
                <lb n="2"/>...
            </ab>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="b">
            <ab>
                <lb n="1"/>...
                <lb n="2"/>...
            </ab>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="c">
            <ab>
                <lb n="1"/>...
                <lb n="2"/>...
            </ab>
        </div>
    </egXML>
    
    <p>In the following example from DHARMA, a set of inscribed copper plates with an inscribed seal attached to the ring that binds the plates together:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DHARMA">        
        <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
            <div type="textpart" n="A">
                <head xml:lang="en">Seal</head>
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>śrī-tribhuvanāṁkuśa
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="B">
                <head xml:lang="en">Plates</head>
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>svasti śrīmatāṁ sakala-bhuvana-saṁstūyamāna-mānavya-sagotrānāṁ 
                    <lb n="2"/>...
                </ab>
            </div>
        </div>
    </egXML>

    <p>These units may, of course, nest in almost any combination. If there are non-hierarchical
        overlaps between units (e.g. sections and columns) then one unit has to be selected as the
        "top level" division, and the other broken up between the larger division. These smaller,
        broken divisions may be connected using the <att>n</att> attribute or a <gi>link</gi>
        element.</p>

    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="i">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="a">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>...
                    <lb n="2"/>...
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="b">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>...
                    <lb n="2"/>...
                </ab>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="ii">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="c">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>...
                    <lb n="2"/>...
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="fragment" n="d">
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1"/>...
                    <lb n="2"/>...
                </ab>
            </div>
        </div>
    </egXML>
    
    <p>Where two distinct texts appear on one support (e.g. two distinct inscriptions on one stone),
        they can either be encoded in one single EpiDoc file or in two separate files. This is an editorial decision and EpiDoc
        does not dictate the use of one method over the other. If encoding the two texts in a single file,
        two separate <gi>div</gi>s with <att>type</att> of "textpart" should be used within the edition division.
        Each translation, commentary, bibliography etc. should also be divided into two textparts in order to record information
        separately about each text. If encoding the texts in two separate files, a link can be provided (or at the least a mention can be made)
        in the commentary directing the reader to the other text that appears on the same support.</p>
    
    <p>When a physical break in the support does not coincide with a major semantic break in the text and
        the physical division of the text does not need to be part of the citation scheme for the text as a whole 
        (for example, multiple blocks in a long relief text, or text split in two consecutive columns), 
        the <gi>milestone</gi> or <gi>cb</gi> or <gi>pb</gi> elements should be used instead to mark the
        point at which a break in the support occurs.</p>
    
    <!--<cit>
        <quote>Section A</quote>
        <bibl corresp="#london"/>
    </cit>

    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#london">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="A"/>
    </egXML>-->
    
    <divGen type="seealso"/>
    
    <div xml:id="trans-textpart-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Scott Vanderbilt</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Charlotte Tupman</name></respStmt></bibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Irene Vagionakis</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
