<!-- Start license statement: do not remove 
    
    EpiDoc: Guidelines for Structured Markup of Epigraphic Texts in TEI
    Edition 8 copyright © 2008–2016 by all contributors listed in <div type="gl-responsibility">, below.
    Additional contributors' copyright may be designated in individual source files.
    
    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
    modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
    as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
    of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
    
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.
    
    Information about the EpiDoc community can be obtained via 
    http://epidoc.sf.net.
    
    End license statement: do not remove -->
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../schema/epidoc.nvdl"?>
<div xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="trans-diplomatic">
    <head>Diplomatic Transcriptions</head>
    
    <p>A diplomatic transcription in epigraphic or papyrological terms is one that records
    only the characters as they appear on the support, with minimal or no editorial intervention
    or interpretation. It differs from a drawing in that individual letters are identified, usually to Unicode codepoints,
    but will often be written in uppercase, without spaces, punctuation or diacritics (unless these are
    in the source document), and without restoring lacunae or expanding abbreviations.</p>
    
    <p>It is generally an assumption in the EpiDoc workflow and tooling that a diplomatic transcription
    can be generated from the underlying XML as an alternative, or parallel, view to the interpretive
    edition following the normal <term target="#leiden">Leiden Conventions</term>. In the 
        <term target="#epidoc-stylesheers">EpiDoc Example Stylesheets</term>
    changing the parameter <code>$edition-type</code> to "diplomatic" will lead the XSLT to
    leave abbreviations unresolved, treat <gi>supplied</gi> elements as <gi>gap</gi>s, transform
    text nodes to uppercase, unaccented, unspaced text, and so forth, creating a fair reproduction
    of what a diplomatic edition is expected to look like.</p>
    
    <p>A few diplomatic features, such as unusually-shaped characters, partially lost letters at
    the ends of lines, internal spacing in Imperial inscriptions, are not terribly well handled by these 
    transformation templates. In addition, some communities may feel that a separate diplomatic
    edition, where different decisions in the transcription are made, would be desirable. This could
    perhaps be encoded as a <tag>div type="edition" subtype="diplomatic"</tag>.</p>

    <div xml:id="trans-diplomatic-responsibility">
        <head>Responsibility for this section</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><respStmt><resp>author</resp><name>Gabriel Bodard</name></respStmt></bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
</div>
